He will be a staff for the righteous with which for them to stand and not to fall and he will be the light of the nations
And the hope of those whose hearts are troubled all who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him and they will praise and
Bless and celebrate with song the Lord of spirits
Firstienok chapter 48 verses 4 through 5 the modern world doesn't acknowledge but is nevertheless
haunted by spirits, angels, demons, and saints in our time.
many year into break free of the prison of a flat secular materialism to see and to
know reality as it truly is. What is this spiritual reality like? How do we
engage with it well? How do we permeate everyday life with spiritual presence?
Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen
De Young host this live Colin show focused on enchantment in creation. The union
of the scene and unseen as made by God.
and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Good evening, all of you out there in Radio Land,
all of you giant killers, dragon slayers,
stretchers of serpents, stompers on scorpions,
whatever's required.
You're listening to the Lord of Spirits podcast.
My co-host, Father Stephen D'Yung,
is with me from Lafayette, Louisiana,
and I'm Father Interestee,
Mandemic in a man's Pennsylvania,
where the leaves are starting to turn,
And we are live.
So if you're listening to us live, you can call us at 855-237-2346 and talk to us.
And we're going to get to your calls in the second half of the show, and Matriska Trudy will be taking your calls.
So the Lord of Spirits podcast is brought to you by our listeners with help from
Lord coffee roasters.
Lord coffee roasters is a specialty coffee company owned and operated by two Orthodox Christian families
working to glorify God in all things.
The lore team is focused on-
and sourcing and roasting the highest quality coffee from all over the earth and having
a delivered to your door in a seamless experience.
They have built a subscription platform on their website, making it easy for you to
choose your coffee, how much of it you would like, how often you want it delivered.
They are also equipped to provide wholesaling solutions for selected partnerships.
Help support Laura Spears by choosing coffee from Laura Coffee Roasters and Orthodox Specialty
coffee company and we parted the story behind Good Coffee.
view their coffee library and subscription plans at lorerosters.com. You can follow them on
Instagram and Facebook at lorecoffeerosters and for 10% off of your first order you can use
the discount code LOS10. So that's LOS10. And I should tell you, you know, everybody, that they sent me
a sample of the coffee, but I don't just want to talk about it. I want to have some coffee.
Pretty good.
Also, probably the only bag of coffee that you buy that has
serif in on the packaging.
So that's kind of cool.
So get your coffee everybody.
That's Laura as an L-O-R-E, which is a good old English word,
meaning knowledge.
Anyway, tonight we are completing the two
part that we started last time, which was all about idolatry
last time.
Tonight's episode is about iconography.
There is a lot of confusion.
out there about the relationship between these two things.
But a lot of people thinking that if you just do over the top icon veneration, then you
can slip over into idolatry.
To a lot of modern people, icons, and idols seem awfully similar.
Are they really though?
Are the Orthodox dancing close to idolatry?
And some poor, illiterate peasants accidentally stepping over the line.
Whoops, you did an idolatry.
To understand that, we need to talk about
iconography. So idolatry and iconography really just have two things in common, right?
Images and religion. Is that right, Father? Um, actually. Already, you know, I'm actually
here at the beginning of the episode. Yes, already. I'm already feeling
be moralized. It's Thursday night, you know what that means.
Um, so.
Yeah, we kind of, we kind of implied that last time.
Yeah. Right.
But as we get into it,
even that is going to break down a little bit.
But so I think a lot of the problem in these discussions
between Orthodox folk and other folk, regarding iconography,
as we mentioned last time is that
These things are seen to be idolatry and iconography are seen to be essentially one phenomenon.
Yeah.
And I think a lot of, for example, our Protestant friends think that this is just word-parcing.
So like when pagans do it, it's called idolatry.
When Jewish people of the Old Testament did it, because they weren't supposed to, it was idolatry.
And then when the Orthodox Church does it, we say,
no, it's iconography.
It's a totally different thing.
Yeah, yeah.
I mean, you get to sense sometimes
with some of the criticisms that were really just trying
to pull a fast one on everybody.
Yeah, yeah.
And what we really have set out to do with these two episodes,
as we mentioned last time,
and I think we'll become increasingly clear now
as we go through the second of the two phenomena,
is that they are separate phenomena.
They are two different things.
So last time we talked about pagan idolatry.
We talked about Israelite idolatry.
We talked about how idolatry still goes on among Christians and in Christian churches.
As a phenomenon.
And now this episode may be unexpectedly to a lot of people.
We're going to talk about pagan iconography.
Wait, what?
Yes.
And Israelite iconography and Christian iconography.
Yeah, cuz-
turns out that iconography and idolatry exists alongside each other in the same community.
There are people who are doing both. Yes. Doing one or not the other. Yeah.
But yes, and this is what you, if these are, as we've been claiming, if these are two separate
phenomena, that is what you would expect to find. Right? You would expect to find both phenomena
existing in a variety of places. It would look a little suspicious.
if everywhere other than the Orthodox Church,
there was this one thing, idolatry,
and then the Orthodox Church,
who were saying, oh no, there's this other thing, iconography.
Yeah.
Right?
But that's not the case, right?
So within idolatrous pagan communities,
there's also iconography.
It's distinguishable from idolatry,
right, as a separate phenomenon even there.
And that's where we're sort of starting out tonight.
But also because of that, I have to, I'm actually you on that introductory point, right?
Because obviously images, visual images are involved in both, right?
Yes, right.
That's not, I'm actually a bull, right?
Yes.
There is artisanship involved in the production of both, right?
But at that point, we're in a really broad range, right?
Right. So I mean, idolatry and pornography are also involved imagery.
Yeah.
There are many, many now distinguishable phenomena involving imagery that everyone would want
to distinguish from one another.
McDonald's happy meals, for instance.
Yes.
I would distinguish, well, you know, to people who have a problem with McDonald's.
Well, I have a certain, I have a certain...
late childhood affection for the happy meal, even though the happy meal is a shadow of what it once was.
That is very true. You don't get these goals, but never more. Yeah, kids will never understand the way
happy meals used to be. Yeah, you don't get the cool box anymore with the puzzles and games on the
outside. No, no. The toy is just like, is cheap as like zero points of articulation and is trying to
to get your parents to take you to see a movie.
Who does even smaller?
Yeah.
And worst of all, from my perspective,
is the whole like, oh, we'll give you apple slices.
It's a French fries.
No one goes to McDonald's for healthy food.
Yes, exact.
Why are you playing?
And, and, and they even betray their own premise
because they give you the apple slices with caramel dip, right?
So like, right, you've already, right?
like.
I didn't know this was the rant we were going to start off with, but here we go.
Yes.
So, you know, the classic happy meal.
Wither the classic happy meal.
Alas.
Yeah.
We hardly knew you.
But yes, so there's other kinds of iconography.
Yes.
So, yeah.
And also, and the, as I was going to say, the other thing is like, the idea that there is
this separate thing called religion is a very modern notion.
Right.
And that's the second category.
they both involved.
religion part. Right. And the problem there is basically, well, it's twofold. On one hand,
it's using this modern category of a religion, right, where religion is sort of its own independent
variable, which is very modern, right? Because in before the modern
period. Identity with a people, with a people group, right, with a tribe, a clan, what gets translated
now somewhat and agronistically as a nation was sort of a holistic kind of identity. So it
involved a way of life, it involved the food you ate, it involved the gods you worshipped
and how you worship them.
It involved a whole cycle of feasts and festivals.
attached to the harvest and things attached to the spring. And all of these things, right,
we're all bound up together as sort of one whole, right? So you talk about the ways of a given people.
And that gets broken down when we get into the modern period. And you start forming what really ends
up forming. There are any number of things that could have potentially been a...
rallying point around which people formed identity.
One of them could have been religion, but the 30 years war happened and
folks in Europe decided that was a bad idea, right? Right. Right.
Yeah, because you had Protestants and Catholics murdering each other.
So what it ended up becoming was nationalism. It ended up becoming the nation's state.
and when it became the nation state.
Right? This means that identity with the nation has to be absolute and then
everything else becomes an independent variable. Religion becomes an
independent variable. For example, you can do that at home if you like. Right.
Politics becomes an independent variable. All these things are second to whatever
you are. Right? You can sort of plug in whatever interreligion. So now we have
this idea of religion or a religion and of religious beliefs and it's mostly
considered in
in terms of beliefs because we're dealing with early modern northern Europe here, so mostly
Protestant.
But also we can throw in practices, religious beliefs and practices as this separate thing.
And so then you can put things in that box.
So if you're approaching it from that view, okay, most of what gets called iconography
in the Orthodox Church, Orthodox iconography would obviously be...
because I had to specify orthodox being the religion basket.
Yeah.
Idolatry would be in the religion basket.
Right.
But iconography is a category without that qualifier.
Covers a whole lot of things.
Right.
So what could that be, Uncle Steve?
Ronald McDonald.
Grimmis.
Not.
Yes.
Grimmis, who somehow is connected to shakes, but that's a whole
other.
Yeah.
I go there.
Right
the time for all my McDonald's rants all at once. I had no idea that you had like a cash
if oh yeah McDonald's rants the whole the whole McDonald's mythos makes no sense.
Makes no sense. I mean the figures are very strangely like the only thing that links them
is that they're putting them together. And the fried guys are the fried guys made of
fries. Yeah. Do they cook the fries? Why are they hanging out with a hamburger who's
He's not gonna eat them as a s**t.
Anyway, okay, back to the topic.
So, Ronald McDonald, Mickey Mouse, right?
This is a G's iconography.
But even more pertinent to the dynamic we were just talking about,
the iconography that becomes sort of foremost during that same period,
including taking to itself a lot of religious iconography is the nation state.
Nationalism sort of adopts iconography and we could all come up with a thousand
examples of this. In the United States obviously there's a lot of prominent
iconography of the nation's state, the American flag. Yeah that's number one.
Right.
I feel like you even got mythological figures like Uncle Sam where you know,
George Washington basically has a logical figure now.
The bald eagle.
Yeah.
Right.
Like, and on and on and on.
And that, while sometimes it has flirted with religion, right?
And we talked last time about how there are, I, dole atriss uses of that sort of
thing, even if we're talking very strictly, the way we talked about the state being able
to become an idol last time is different than just viewing the iconography of the state.
Yeah.
Right. So there's a difference between making the American state an idol where it's what
you're putting your trust in, right?
And it's what you see is as having the power to control your destiny, right?
And...
going to a firework show on the 4th of July.
And I think we know intuitively that these are different things.
Yeah.
Right.
I think we know intuitively the difference between those two.
One can certainly do both, right?
But it's also possible to do one or the other.
There's a good book about this called Earthly Powers
that has a lot of photos and visual examples.
showing religious iconography in Europe from before the French Revolution and then the way in the 19th century leading up to World War I,
the various nation-states of Europe started adopting and repurposing a lot of that religious iconography as iconography of the state.
And I will go ahead and throw this out there.
So, in addition to thinking that idolatry and iconography are sort of this one single phenomenon,
right, another part of the related criticism is that veneration and worship are the same thing.
Yeah, yeah, I mean, you can even see like mocking memes, usually aimed at Catholics God,
You know saying it's just quote unquote then
generation like we all know that you're worshiping Mary, but you're just calling
Admineration, you know, yeah, because either those are the same thing or they're on a plane,
right? Yeah, like you said last time you've inter a too hard and do an idolatry.
But allow me to submit, especially if you're one of those folks,
since we just brought up the iconography of the state.
So when someone goes to a ballgame,
And right before the ball game begins, they stand up and they put their hand over their heart.
And they stand and look at an icon of the nation state, namely the American flag.
And they sing him about how beautiful and wonderful America is.
Is that veneration or worship?
Right.
I'm not saying this to say it's worship.
I'm saying this is a generation.
They are venerating the flag.
Right?
But so, if you need an intuitive place, if the religious place isn't intuitive enough
for you to make that distinction, the distinction doesn't make sense in your gut, here's a place
where I think it will.
Yeah, or I mean like another example I like to give is the way that people.
will behave in cemeteries.
Traditionally, people go in there, they go quiet.
They come up to the grave of their loved one.
They might put flowers there.
They might talk to that person at the grave.
They certainly would not spit on it or,
you know, desecrate, like they wouldn't treat it
disrespectfully.
Like there's a sense that I need to treat this rock
respectfully, right?
And yet...
There's not a sense of, oh, I'm worshipping this dead spirit.
Everybody knows that's not the same thing as the ancestor worship.
Yeah.
If I put, you know, flowers next to this or light a candle next to it, you know, or whatever, it's not ancestor worship.
An ancestor worship is a thing, but it's a different thing.
It's not that thing.
Yeah.
That's not the thing it is.
For a minute, there I was worried that you're going to talk about how people behave in seminaries, which
So
scandalous for a whole part is involved. There is a lot of overlap.
In my experience, no, there isn't people are very respectful in cemeteries.
Oh, I was talking about the death part, but oh, okay, it will bury you.
There are people who are sad. Yes, there's a lot of meeping. It's true occasional gnashing of teeth. Weeping numb teeth.
So
That said,
right, that iconography is not purely a religious phenomenon, right?
And so really the only connection between the two phenomena of idolatry and iconography is that they both involve images, right?
What then, if we're going to talk about, like last time we talked about the phenomenon of idolatry,
sort of in its origins, how it works.
We're going to try it tonight now for the rest of the night to talk about do the same for iconography and hopefully along the way
Everybody will if they don't already start seeing the the difference that these are two different things the difference between these two
Phenomena and so to get into iconography and its origins
We have to talk about the relationship between myth and image
Hmm.
And to talk about the relationship between myth and image, we kind of have to define myth first.
Let's do a little bit review everybody.
Yeah, so we have talked about this before but I think it's been a while.
So unless you're one of those folks who's a long haul trucker and just did their fifth,
re-listen to the whole, the entire show, what 200 plus hours of it.
Two hours.
Which is a thing.
thing. I mean we hear from some long haul truckers that have listened to this. Yeah. Yeah.
So those folks will be familiar, but for everybody else.
So myth, right, a myth, mythos literally means story, right, in Greek, but it's not just any story.
It's a particular type of story. It's a story that has a sort of ongoing life.
sort of ongoing life.
Anybody can write stories, anybody can make up stories.
anybody can relate events in the past from our perspective as a story, right? But
Ameth is a story that has a particular ongoing significance and it has that
ongoing significance within a community, a community of people, right? So Ameth is
not just a story that like so I might have a story about me and my dad doing
something when I was a kid that has ongoing significance to me.
Yeah.
Right.
But that doesn't have, and maybe even to some of my family members, but that's not really
a myth, right?
It becomes a myth when it has an ongoing importance to a wider community.
That story from my childhood, while it might be interesting or even have some valuable
lesson for the people saying in my parish, right?
if I used to it as a sermon illustration or something.
On a Sunday.
That story would not be a story that they then go and repeat and gets repeated and goes on for generations.
And if it did, it would become a myth.
So that's that it would be a myth.
Right. So that ongoing significance means it continues to be passed down generally, generationally.
Yeah.
And it continues to have a ritual life.
And we'll talk about that more here in a second.
Bye.
But it's important.
We also mentioned the difference between myth and mythology.
Yeah.
Mythology is basically when the participation drops out, and it's no longer a story that
kind of defines a people.
It's sort of just a story.
Right.
A myth dies.
And so now you can dissect it.
Yeah.
Now you can look at it, take it apart, try to figure out how it worked.
Right.
purpose.
it was serving, you can compare it to other stories. You can see it as a half-life somewhere
else or something. But by that point, it is dead.
Yeah, it's not like it's not a driving force behind who your community is.
Right. So this is this is the difference between reading Homer in the second century BC and
reading Homer today. Yeah, exactly. Right.
or reading Hesiod and reading Edith Hamilton's mythology.
Right. These are different things.
And it's from the latter category mythology
that the common modern use of myth
to mean something not true comes from.
Right, like people say, that's just a myth.
Right.
And so mythology, it is true that mythology isn't true.
because it's not true anymore, because it has no connection to the real world of
existing people anymore. But all myths while they're alive have at least a
certain kind of truth to them. That doesn't mean they're quote unquote literally
true, right, or you know, strap on a GoPro and get an atartist, right, like you
you could find a place
these events actually happened exactly the way they happened in a particular telling of the story
that not that modern kind of truth, which as we've said, that kind of objective idea of truth
doesn't actually exist. But a truth in that the story actually had an effect in the world
through its ritual life and the lives of actual people who exist in the world. And it shaped and
been motivated there.
actions in the world in a way that produce those effects. And that's real. So that's true,
right? In that sense. Yeah, I mean, it's an actual experience people are really having.
Yes. Yeah. Yeah. So as we said, the way in which myth, the life, this myth has life in
this community.
people in this ongoing, even generational way, is through ritual. And we've talked about
ritual before. This is a broad definition of ritual, right? Ritual is obviously repeated
behavior, right? And in this case, repeated communal behavior, there's some very obvious
ways in which myths get ritualized. Probably the most obvious is ritual storytelling.
Right, there's a time and place in circumstance repeatedly in which that story is told.
And he's generally told by a particular person and told even in a particular way.
Now when I say in a particular way, I do not mean that all the details are the same in each telling.
Right. Right.
So, you could read...
I mean, you can read if you're a nerd.
You read sociological studies of storytelling
in oral based cultures, right?
And they found, for example, that you can have to start,
like I said, there's usually a particular person who does this,
whether that person is some kind of what we would call
clergy figure, or whether it's a paternal figure who
tells the story or...
whomever, right? There's generally a designated storyteller and you can take it in oral culture to
designated storytellers who regularly tell the same story and
Where one tells the story and it's say
45 minutes long in his telling and another one tells it and it's 25 minutes long in his telling
You can have the 45 minute long storyteller listen to the 25 minute storyteller and
and ask him.
So did he get the story right?
And he'll say yes.
They'll ask him, did he leave anything out?
Nope.
And of course, the Western people doing this study, the sociologist are like, you left out
like 20 minutes man for the wage challenge.
Like, what do you mean you didn't leave anything out?
Yeah, yeah.
Because we think quantitatively about these kinds of things.
Right.
And we're not in oral based culture.
Right, a story.
This pile of stuff, this exact pile of stuff.
Yeah.
You know, whereas like, I mean, like a really good example,
for instance, since you mentioned Northern Europe earlier,
you know, there's a story called the Vulsing Asaga,
the saga of the Vulsings.
And there are multiple versions of it
in different Germanic languages,
and they do not all line up.
Like you can't make them work perfectly with each other.
And yet that set of traditions is the Vulsing Asaga.
know, it just it just is even though the details are not are not exactly the same from one
version to another. Right. Right. And that it's fundamentally different once you get to a
text-based society. Yeah. Right. Right. So now Peter Jackson comes along and tells a story
and everybody's like, bro, you left out Tom Bommadill. How dare you start? Yes.
What's up?
Right.
So, that's because there's a written text.
Yeah, right.
that people can look at?
There's a written text people could refer to and say, you left out this.
This is now the real version of the story because it's been enshrined in text, right?
But in oral culture there isn't, right?
So the way of telling a story that I'm talking about that makes it ritual is not all the
details and all the words being the same words in the same order, right?
But it's the overall thrust and purpose of the story.
Yeah
Because remember, ritual does something.
So the telling of this story is supposed to do something.
It's supposed to create a state of consciousness in the people who are participating in the
storytelling.
And so if it does that, then it has been done correctly.
If it fails to do that, then there's been a failure somewhere in the process.
So yeah, ritual storytelling is the most obvious.
right way of which a story could be ritualized I think.
But also, of course, this includes reenactment.
Yeah.
Very swarms of ritual reenactment of the story.
Doing things like, you know,
a Palm Sunday procession.
To write a reenactment.
Right.
Or the Passover meal.
Yeah.
Everyone dresses as if they're about to flee from Egypt,
even if they're living in Brooklyn, right?
Like you're reenacting this thing
and thereby participating.
in it in that story.
But also something we may not think about
singing the story.
Most of these stories, Homer, right.
These were sung.
And taking something and singing it
rather than saying it in sort of a prose style
serves to elevate it.
serves to give it a different character.
Right. To the public participation in it and yields new ways. Right. If you think about
someone, you know, picks up a guitar, picks up a piano. Yeah. Put it down. Put it down,
Yeah, it starts to sing something.
The fact that they're singing, the people who are around that person are able to
participate in that in a different way than if he just started telling a story.
Even if you don't know the words, you'll kind of get the hang of the melody
after a while.
And so singing a story is another way to ritualize it.
sort of in this way, in this collective setting. But your main to our topic tonight,
another way of richly reenacting a story is through visual depiction.
Yeah, painted on the wall, painted on a panel, make it into a statue,
you carve it in a freeze, because then when someone, the viewer or the group or the
people stand in front of it and look at it, they are reconnected with that story if it's
a story they know.
Or in particularly well done iconography, it can tell the story all by itself, even if
they don't know it.
Or it could be used in conjunction with the telling of a story.
So, and so this is there's ritual activity on both sides of producing iconography.
The production of it is a ritual activity because you are taking right that story and you
are giving it visual form in the same way that telling it or singing it.
Right? Or participating and acting it out would be a ritual activity. Right? That's giving
reality and ongoing life to that story. And then on the other side, those who are viewing it,
right? There isn't an ongoing ritual activity there. Right? And
these are not right. So this is part of why we had to disambiguate the religion thing.
at the beginning, right? Because of course in the ancient world these things aren't separated
and the modern world they are, but when big groups of people get together to see the same movie
over and over again in theaters, right? It's a ritual. They're doing this same thing.
And sometimes depending on the movie they might like dress in a special way.
Yes, I could go to a Star Wars
premiere you will allow allow me to be the first one I think in the history of
ancient faith to mention the Rocky Horror picture show on air. Oh yes.
Yes. I can't wait to know anything about that. But to which people have been going
to midnight shows for decades, dressing up as characters. They've memorized all the lines.
Yep. Yep. Right. And this is ritual activity.
This is stuff that's built into how we work as human.
In some cases, they'll even have a cast acting out the thing on a stage while the movie's
playing.
Yeah.
So this is all, this is all functional ritual activity, right?
So as Christians, we believe that like all properly human activity, right, it has its
ultimate focus on bringing us closer to God, and that's its correct usage.
Right. It's correct usage, the correct usage of ritual, including iconography is, right,
to bring us closer to God. But because it is properly human, it is kind of ubiquitous.
And could be used for all kinds of things. Good and bad. But any of these ritual functions are
unavoidable because they're built into us and how we function as humans.
So, when we...
look, now going back all the way back. It's been a while since we did this in the first half
going all the way back to the Neolithic era. It's true. It's been a while. We talk about
visited those sites in Turkey and Syria again. Yeah.
We're talking about the origins of pagan iconography.
The earliest kind of things we see are in the early
human settlements we've found. So as always, my proviso, if you think this is older than the earth
is, adjust accordingly. It's fine. It's fine. It's not about the dates. We love just about everybody
here at Lord of Spirits. I'll say that for myself. Father Andrew probably loves everybody.
I probably love about five more people than you do. Probably. Yeah. Now he only loves everybody
because God says He has to.
BUS!
I don't like everybody.
Yeah, I do think he actually loves everybody, unlike me.
But the earliest site, the common dating of Go Beckley-Tepi is about 10,000 BC.
And we've talked about it before.
Go Beckley-Tepi is this oldest known human site.
but we've also talked about it in the context of the
fact that this begins as a site of religious pilgrimage and only later becomes a human settlement.
So this begins as a place where nomadic people assemble at certain times of the year
for religious ritual and then eventually develop sort of a standing community
as the neolithic revolution progresses and people begin to be able to plant and harvest crops.
So
So the standing stones that we have at Gobekli Teppi that seems to have served an astrological
purpose have reliefs card into them and their animal forms.
I think there's a human form or two also, but mostly animals.
And so here, earliest known...
verifiably religious sight in the world, again, however you want to date it, has iconography.
And these are reliefs and forms carved into standing stones used for astrological observation.
Yeah, kind of a stone hinge of sorts.
So these are not like an idol at the center of a shrine like we talked about last.
time. There's no alter next to them. Yeah. Yeah. So there's no, no evidence of any ritual activity
directed toward these images. Yeah. And they're like relatively speaking off to the side, you know,
as compared to as you said, like an idol at the center of a shrine. Right. And so this is why we're
categorizing this as pagan iconography. This is within a sacred space and attached.
to a sacred space and clearly for the people who put it there, part of what makes it sacred
space but is not the object of ritual and worship.
Yeah, and it's not the focal point.
Right.
And if you want to go back potentially earlier than that, again, not arguing about dates with
anybody, we have Neanderthal caves in Spain and France.
other Neanderthal caves because there's deanderthal bones there. I'm also as someone who is an
other Neuropean possesses a large amount of Neanderthal DNA, not going to argue about that whole thing.
So our cousins, yes. So these are my forefathers. And by that, I mean, you're as a my cousin's not
You know, human. Yeah, yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Some of you may have no Neanderthal DNA whatsoever, but
I got some relatives back there.
Apparently Neanderthals, based on the shape of their throat,
had incredibly high pitched voices.
Wow.
Which just fascinates me.
Give an article.
Visual image of a Neanderthal.
I feel like there's a Michael Jackson reference
we can make here that it's just not coming to me,
but that's okay.
Yeah.
But in reference to our topic this evening,
That's in these the inner thought case.
And again, we know they're Neanderthal caves because there's dead Neanderthals there.
They're buried there.
Yeah.
Right.
So, you know, whatever you want to say about Neanderthals, they buried their dead.
Which is interesting.
Yeah.
Which kind of points toward humanity, I would say.
is an activity that we would now put in the religion basket.
Right. And accompanying these burial sites is some of the earliest iconography we have,
which is paint on cave walls, which we could tell from handprints in some of these cave walls,
was done by a person dipping their finger-slash hand in some kind of dye or resin.
and then using it to make animal forms and human forms.
on walls. Which also sounds like human behavior to me, just for the record.
And so the whole development of idolatry that we trace last time
and the beginnings of the developments of iconography that we've just started tracing this time,
these are things that are happening contemporaneously.
Right.
There are two parallel tracks here at the beginning.
Yeah, because I mean, there's the earliest known stuff.
Yeah.
The humans.
So going tracing both of these back to the Neolithic era,
they're two separate parallel things.
Right, so if you wanna hypothesize
some kind of convergence
in some kind of even earlier prehistoric era,
go ahead but you got no evidence to go on.
Yeah, I mean, there's nothing that has been dug up yet.
Yeah. So we see something similar, right? These two things existing in parallel at Kettlehoek,
the other super ancient site that we talked about, we've talked about in the past when we're
we're talking about the origins of pagan religion
in Kailhoi in the dwellings.
near the place. So in the dwellings in Kettle Hoek, when someone in the family died, they were buried
in the, quote unquote, floor, because it's a dirt floor of the family home. They were buried sort of underneath the house.
Um, there by continuing to recognize them as part of the family in some ongoing way.
So again, this is clearly religious activity.
And near the portion of these dwellings,
where there are these burials in the homes,
there are bull horns mounted on walls, usually on walls.
And those bull horns are clearly iconography.
Yeah, I can talk about this before.
connected to the the bull worship.
that is kind of the url level of idolatry
in almost every single world culture.
Yeah, which we connected to
where we talked about the he-meth, the he-mote,
right, bowl of heaven, bowl, bail.
We talked about all these things.
So you have those, right?
But that is not like a full on idol
because there are elsewhere in the site,
there are sort of bull statues, statues of bulls.
That we're being used as idols. Yeah, because there's altars near their evidence of sacrifices being offered there
Right, so in Kettlehoek there's idolatry going on with a bowl, right?
But there's also
religious iconography connected to that going on, right, but it is a distinguishable phenomenon
Right and that iconography that's going on with the horns is
is attached to
the place where what we would today call private or family worship or whatever
whatever practices are going on whatever religious ritual practices are going on
in the home are happening there with the I can where the iconography is right so
it's still religious iconography again but it's not that the horns aren't the
same thing as an idle because there are idles.
And they could have, right?
We could have found small clay bull statues
instead of the antlers.
And the private homes, right?
In which case we would say,
oh, that was idolatry, right?
So this, of course, develops over millennia slash centuries.
And what becomes very
very common, the most common iconography in the ancient Near East, whether we're talking
about Egypt or we're talking about Babylonian civilization, a Syrian civilization, even
into the Persian period.
The most common thing we find are reliefs.
So carved images in walls or painted images on walls.
like both of those we find in Egypt.
Sometimes the painted ones are now gone for a variety of reasons.
I mean mostly because paint doesn't last forever.
Yeah. And many of the ones that were carved also had paint on them at one point.
So we don't know whether that paint was just enhancing the carved figures or whether there
would have been additional information if the paint was still there.
Right. Like if there were inscriptions or other figures that weren't carved
We've got work.
painted around the carved figures. That's not something super noble, but we find...
That's incredibly commonly. It mostly moves in the Greek and Roman period to painted frescoes.
There tends to be less wall carving and more wall painting when you get into Greek civilization and
and the Romans basically kind of do great...
great value, Greek civilization.
Yeah.
And I mean, like their whole thing.
Most of us, when we think of the ancient classical world, we think of, you know, big white pillars
and marble buildings, but and statues even.
But these things actually were mostly painted.
Like it would have been very polygons.
You know, ancient Rome was not gleaming white buildings.
It was, it was, yeah, it was painted.
Yeah.
covered in paint brightly colored paint.
Yeah, yeah.
Statues were covered in brightly colored paint.
The ones we now see is just sort of marble.
And we know that not just from finding paint samples
on things, but I mean places like Pompeii
that are pretty well preserved, right?
We can see that just about every inch of the inside
and outside of buildings, including people's homes,
were just covered in frescoes.
Yeah.
We're just covered in imagery.
And...
The greater portion of this imagery was depicting scenes and figures from myth.
Yes.
Right on the one.
And many of them were quite obscene.
Yes.
There's a lot of Goose Zeus.
By our standard.
That's a reader understand.
Goose Zeus.
Sort of the listener, I guess, readers of the transcript.
Yes, Goose Zeus.
Yes, or the origin of the Minotaur.
See, a big euphemistic here.
So, yes, so there's just these depictions, right?
And they're everywhere.
They're on every wall, right?
It's like a teenager's bedroom with posters, right?
Like, so it's not like you can isolate and say,
Oh, okay, right, like we talked about last time with idolatry.
Here's the hearth, here's a center, here's where they have the images of the household gods.
Here's where they come to do religious activity. That's going on.
But also, this pagan iconography is all over the entire house.
So this makes a very clear distinction.
Yeah, and it's not like sacrifices are being offered next to all the walls.
Yeah, like it's not like sacrifice being offered everywhere and oh by the way there's this one one place as a
Statue in it. What's what with that? Yeah, you know, it's clear
This is the sacrificial spot. This is where the worship it happens and there's also this other imagery
Right so the fresco of goose Zeus
Has Zeus is a goose and Zeus is a pagan god
Right, so
Religious iconography, but there's no
The family worship, the offering of saguas, the offering of insides.
primarily in the home is not happening over there, right? That's in the
latrine. It's happening at the hearth. Yeah. Where the where the idols are, right?
So not just these aren't just distinguishable phenomena, these are distinct
phenomena, right? Anyone who lived in one of these homes, any one of these people
in the ancient world.
knew the difference. They weren't confused. They weren't like, hey, why do we go over
there where you have the little statue of Zeus? Instead of just standing here next to the
picture of Zeus? They intuitively knew the difference between an idol and this iconography that
surrounded them. Even when it's depicting the exact same figures. Right?
the exact same divide in figures. These are two different things. And everyone in the ancient world
just understood it because both were going on simultaneously. Both had their own traditions, both
had their own thing. Now I said most of it is scenes from myth. Of course, scenes in persons from
myth. There's also then depictions of family members. So sometimes depictions of family members
in the pagan world.
cross over into the quote unquote religion category. Right? Meaning unambiguously, if we were
going to do the modern basket thing, we'd put them in the religion basket. I mean, one can say,
having a depiction of a part of departed loved one is always kind of there's always sort of a
religious element to it, right? Like yeah, you have to have a very strict definition of religion, but
Right what I mean?
by that is sometimes we're dealing with, you know, your great great great great great great grandfather who founded the city.
Yeah. Right. Who has a shrine adjoining the God's temple.
Right. And you have a depiction of him in your house. Right. So that's that's clearly one kind of thing. Right.
But there's also just there comes to be a cross of wide variety of cultures. This isn't ubiquitous.
But it was a wide variety of cultures you have people making
masks which sometimes are plaster masks of various modes of creation made from dead bodies.
Yeah, like they may put like a dead person put plaster on their face, wait for it to kind of
harden and then pull it off. Right. And sometimes when a person is embalmed and wrapped for burial,
these would be painted onto the wrappings of the face.
to attempt to make it resemble the person.
Or there's like, you know, super stylized ones,
like the ones you see in Egyptian royal burials.
Right.
King Tutankham and so forth.
Yeah.
But this development then also led
to the parallel development of keeping images
of departed loved ones.
And sometimes just keeping them on the walls.
And this was, and I know-
this is gonna date me but when I was a kid we had these things called cameras and
you couldn't call or text on them and not only that but you had to like take it
with you and then you'd aim at it things and push a button and it would take
photos and you weren't sure what they looked like right you didn't know if it was
good or bad at the no idea later he can tell you had a lot of that
Yeah, and you had to go and take it to a place or mail it to a place, right?
This role of film from inside the camera.
And they would then develop that film and send you copies of all the pictures along with the negatives.
So you could get more copies made.
And half the time they all stunk.
It's true.
They were all lit wrong or you know someone was moving or everybody had their eyes closed.
in the photo right and there was nothing you could do because this is like three
weeks later now that you got the photos. I know times were strange in the past
but when that was the case people kept photo albums. They had big books of all
those photos. Go check with your grandparents kids. That phrase is still used
like on Facebook they have an album.
Yes.
Yes, we have to clarify.
These were physical books.
Yes, you could flip through, yeah.
Sometimes with faux leather covers.
Indeed.
With little pages, with little plastic pockets
into which you would slide the paper photographs.
So you could mage through them.
Getting me an eye on the wheels right now.
Yeah.
So.
But very commonly the purpose these served,
these effectively served was.
I'm going to go look at the pictures of my kids when they were little.
I'm going to go look at the pictures of my departed loved ones.
Yeah.
And at some level you feel like you're there again.
Or maybe you weren't there when the thing happened,
but you are participating in some indirect way.
Yeah.
Or this is some time in the past, right?
Some trip.
So you know, I can't say, oh, here, you know.
Yeah, and so again, this is one of those very human things, right?
One of these very human things.
And so we find in a lot of the iconography these images of people, right, who are now gone,
as a means of sort of preserving them, which is its own kind of mythic activity, right?
of keeping them alive, right within the context of the fa-
family as community. So because of this relationship between, as we said, pun intended iconography
draws together a story and sort of reality, right? Sort of people, the viewer and the event,
viewer and the person, right, pull them together in unites the
When we're talking about looking at an interpreting iconography, pagan or otherwise, we've got
to move past a lot of modern categories in order to understand it in this ritual kind
of context, right?
So a lot of us having our head and we went after this and the how to read the Bible episode,
And I'm sure we're going to have to do a sequel to that episode.
because that topic comes up a lot.
Probably a good idea.
We're going to have to do how to read the Bible to Electric Bougaloo.
But we have to get past like the categories of literal versus allegorical.
Right? Because it's not going to make sense.
Right, no one who was standing there
in their parlor looking at the fresco of goose Zeus was like hmm are they trying
to say that Zeus literally became a goose? You know Zeus goose is going to be the
big takeaway for a lot of people from the same so yes yes goose Zeus yeah right
was was goose actually was actually a goose was a goose actually Zeus in top
Top Gun 1 was good weight.
Does Dr. Zeus have a goose? No. So yeah, they were saying they're wondering when was this?
Anybody got a date on when Zeus became a goose and how long was he a goose? And where exactly was this?
And right, so no one was trying to figure out if it was literal. And also there was not someone standing next to him arguing, oh no, no.
Oh no no, goo Zeus is an allegory. You see the goose represents.
right at the back.
That's not at all how this works.
Right? That's not how this works.
And that is this whole idea we have of on the one hand real.
Like is this real or is this symbolic?
Right?
Somewhere Jonathan Peugeot just heard the sound of a billion voices screaming
screaming and then suddenly cut off because.
I use the word symbolic to mean not real.
But that's how it's used by a lot of folks today.
It comes out of eucharistic debates.
It's just a symbol.
That's not how people thought about these things.
that the iconography is a means of communicating a spiritual reality.
a reality that can be participated in, that can be
ritually participated in.
Yeah, it's not just sort of studied.
You're part of it, it's part of you in some way.
Right.
And so, this means that the kind of viewing
that has always been done with iconography,
that's part of what makes an iconography,
Right, is that it's an active kind of viewing.
It is an active viewing of meditation upon the image of becoming present in the event
or with the person portrayed in the image.
Yeah, I mean, it should even be said, like even within the Orthodox Church, sure people
do venerate and we'll talk about this more but we people do venerate icons by
Bye.
seeing them by doing various things, but most of the experience of an icon is in looking
at it. It's the visual contact.
Active viewing is most of what the word veneration means. That's most of what we're talking about
when we talk about veneration. And that's very different than worshiping. That's not
playing with worshiping something.
That's not it is a fundamentally different activity. Yeah, right. No one thinks that someone is
worshiping a movie by viewing it in an active way and getting it quote unquote getting into it.
Or quote unquote getting involved in it. Right. Yeah. That doesn't mean there's nothing wrong with
doing that with certain movies. There certainly is. Right. Right. Right. Or doing that with
with pornography, there's certainly something wrong with that.
Yes, very, very wrong.
Right.
But that is an activity of veneration, not of worship,
and it's an activity that's being misdirected to the wrong object.
Yeah.
Right.
And that's, that is a, being part of what makes it different.
Indeed.
All right. Well, our first half was about pagan iconography,
and our second half is going to be about isoralite iconography
just to give it away.
But before we get to that, we're going to go ahead and take our first break.
So we'll be right back with more Lord of Spirits.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment to take your
calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
Ancient Faith Radio is brought to you by our listeners.
from Faith Tree Resources. Have you ever felt distracted or disengaged in
church but weren't quite sure what to do about it? Divine Liturgy, the greatest
invitation, is the newest video course brought to you from Faith Tree Resources
and will help you better understand and experience the peace God offers to us in
the Divine Liturgy. This four-part series taught by some of the church's most
respected leaders will equip you with resources and tools to help you more
deeply encounter the one true God.
Whether you're a parent, hungry to teach your children,
a pastor looking to equip your faithful,
or someone who wants to learn how to actively
be present in the divine liturgy, this course is for you.
Go to faithtree.org to get your copy today.
That's faithtree.org.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits,
the Father Andrew Stephen Damick, and Father Stephen
DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-845-845.
237-2346. That's 855-AF radio.
Thanks for that voice of Steve. It's the second half of the Lord of Spirits
podcast here on October 12. Two weeks from today we're at the Lord of
Spirits conference. Are you pumped, Father Stephen?
I guess.
I mean, sure.
hahaha
With my play travel luckily, hopefully Lord willing, I'll be there Thursday.
Just as soon as you said that Ellie at a heart attack somewhere, she's this podcast but
I mean, I gotta be honest, you know.
Ellie who is running the whole event and doing a glorious job so far, even though it hasn't started yet.
Yeah.
So yeah, hopefully I also got to figure out what I'm going to say
That would be nice. Let me let me give a tease though. Let me give a tease though to everybody
Like months ago I said in a topic of what I was going to talk about I'm not talking about anything remotely related to that topic
But I'm pretty sure there's nobody out there who bought a ticket who was like I'm only going because father Steven said he's talking about this particular topic
Yeah
I'm really interested in the rise topics.
Yes, that's the oil.
I'm coming if I receive a talk about something different I'm gonna be mad in demandery. I'm out
So yeah, so I don't think that's gonna happen. So yeah, plus it's me
Like you not listen to the show right you expect and
I should say
There's at least as of this moment. There are some some spaces that have opened up so
It's late in the game folks, but if you send a desperate but respectfully worded email
to Ellie.
at ancientfaith.com.
You might be able to still come.
I'm just putting that out there.
So.
Does she want flattery and or bribes?
Ellie is a very, very tough person, actually.
She is very kind, she's very nice,
but she is very, very tough.
So I don't think you can sway her with stuff like that.
Anyone can be swayed by a big enough bribe.
Mm.
It's just a matter of what the price is.
Like I'm pretty sure if someone offers her $10 million,
like she'll be like,
You can have...
I don't know.
Okay, yeah.
Please make a donation.
Right.
You guy who's willing to pay $10 million to get a room
with his technically one or two available.
I mean, we should look at him.
He really wants to be there.
Yeah, so yeah, before we dive into Israel like iconography,
this is a live call and show.
And we in fact do have a live caller
on the other end of the line.
We have Daniel calling from Florida. Daniel, welcome to Lord of Spirits podcast
Hello fathers. This is Florida man and friend of the show the Danimal
Florida man
I do hope that this is a live color because it's too early in October for the dead to start to call in
Oh, no, this is one of many Florida men
But I do have a serious question about iconography and then a follow-up question.
depending on how the first was answered.
Okay, if it's hard, we're going to punt it to Pazzo.
Okay.
Maybe the second question.
I don't know.
We'll start with the easy one.
So I traveled to Metteora and Athens earlier in the year and I noticed a particular icon,
but I said, huh, that doesn't seem right.
There we go.
looking at some of the cannons of the church, it seemed to violate the...
Canons of the St.
Ecumenical Council.
So it was one of the father depicted as an old white man and beard Christ and the Holy Spirit.
I did happen to see the earliest icon I could find of it was in the 1500s by like at one of the museums there.
So my question is, if you're going to a parish
and you see something that clearly violates the canons,
like...
What is the proper response you just go to the priest afterwards kind of like in Matthew like a the priest really hate
I don't think we should actually have this up here or like you know
What is the proper response when you find stuff that clearly violates the rules on that
Set it ablaze
That was gonna be my joke. No, sorry. No, no see
That's my first reaction, but I'm like
There's something that seems wrong about breaking an image, right?
Yeah.
world-broken images. So maybe someone can just rewrite it and salvage it.
Yeah. I mean, so I mean the reality and we talked about this was this, I'm trying to remember,
this was like one of our earliest episodes, I think when we were doing the the Christology series,
right? When we did, we were talking about the the Son of Man and the Ancient of Days and so forth.
I don't remember which one that was father, but
But yeah, so
Here's a reality, there are rules against depicting God the Father in Orthodox iconography.
There are many icons that depict God the Father in Orthodox iconography.
I mean, you saw him on Matero.
I saw him all over Mount Athos.
Like, they've got him in lots of places on Mount Athos.
And you know, you want to know one that's even weirder.
There is a quote, Trinity icon that exists on Athos, where it's basically, you know,
a man with three face.
I mean, that is way weirder than the old men with a white beard.
What do you do about that?
I mean, here's the thing.
If you're not the bishop of that parish, which presumably you're not.
Yeah, I don't know.
I'm at the bottom of the totem pole.
I'm pretty sure the janitor has a higher pecking order than I do.
So yeah.
I mean, there is...
There are a couple of bishops here in the United States named Daniels, but you don't sound
like either one of them.
I've met both of them.
If you're not the bishop, even if it is a real problem, it's not your responsibility.
It's just not.
You haven't mind this, right?
I've been to parishes where things happen.
I'm like, oh, what's going on here?
Nope, not my-
because not my monkeys. That's just a reality. You're going to see things that happen in churches
that are off. If you're on Manatos, would you say, excuse me, I need to find the habit. I have
to report this. No, because that's not your job. You're not the one responsible. There's a lot of
things that are off in this world. Unless you're the one responsible for writing it, then you're probably
on the
to make things worse by attempting to do that. I don't know. Father Steven, do you have
anything you want to add besides, you know, set it on fire? Yeah, I've gone on record
with that. But yeah, the, the, so where this actually came from, there's really good book
about this called the image of God the Father and the North of the X-Rition.
even bigger.
Bingham Bingham.
Yeah, is they there was an earlier icon
called the paternity that was an icon that depicted Abraham and Isaac
Hmm with Isaac sitting on Abraham's lap
That was very is very similar to the way you'll see icons of
Uh
Christ as a child sitting on the lap of the Theotokos
But the idea was sort of like
Rubelab's Trinity icon was see Abraham and Isaac this represents
Right sort of the paternity of God the Father, right God the Son
emphasis on the represents and then over time
That whole represents
Thing faded off into the background
And the way you track that fading off into the background is that you start getting different kinds of
halos or nimbuses on the two figures. So it stops being two nimbuses for saints
like Abraham and Isaac and starts to turn into nimbus with the cross in it on
the child, right, that it's Christ. And then under Western influence you get the
throw in a bird and now it's the trinity thing. When these things
show up at my parish as they do occasionally. They end up in my office. I'm actually sitting right next to a few of them right now
on public display.
That's right. You start you know, mosing around in the storage areas of the church. You find all kinds of
things. So yeah, and I mean beyond, I mean what Father Andrew said is correct when you're someplace like Wadathas.
Yeah, like you gotta kind of know your role and shut your mouth.
But in in in parish life, it can get really thorny and naughty, right?
Because for example, the priest of the parish, your aunt that has one of those on public display may hate the thing and want to, you know, bury it somewhere.
But I'll be waiting waiting for the donors don't write exactly, but it was donated by some prominent family in the church.
So he kind of can't write for the sake of the piece of the
community. And by the way, I'm not saying that priest is a wimp. I'm saying that priest is probably in that case exercising good pastoral judgment.
Because the goal of a priest in a church is not to enforce a list of rules. What? The role of a priest in a church is to help the actual humans who make up that parish fine salvation.
Yep.
And so sometimes what they need to help them find Salvee.
is some mercy and some grace with some things that aren't technically correct.
Confronting everything wrong isn't always the best way to handle these things.
Or as our dogmanics professor at St. Tekons would say,
you got to be cool like St. Basil.
You remember that you remember? I don't know.
I don't know man, that's not my notes.
Nice, thank you for that call back.
Sorry, we're doing
in jokes on the air here, Dan.
I'm sorry about that, but we never do that on this show.
I apologize.
Just please just keep being yourself.
Yeah.
So that's a thing now at this point.
And you've got places where, for example,
they've got, I could argue, you've got the father
painted up in a dome.
Yeah.
Where it's going to cost thousands of dollars
to change that.
And this kind of thing.
So...
things have happened, they're not correct. Lots of good folks are out there trying to work
over time, pastoral to correct them. And so we've all got to just show each other a little grace
while that happens. There you go. So you said you had a follow-up question, Daniel? Yes, and actually
spot of Andrew, you kind of lead into that weird image of God with three faces.
So, I'm not saying we...
make an icon of this, but I've been thinking when you're trying to describe the Trinity,
right? Like St. Patrick used the Three Leaks clover. Well, most kids don't even go outside
or know what grass feels like under their feet. We don't know what a clover is. But what about
King Adora from Godzilla? It's got three heads. It's always referred to in the finger. It's
King Adora. Is this really William Lane Craig?
That.
Do William Lane...
Craig called the show under the suit name.
Is that an appropriate or a heretical analogy for the training?
I'm going to all analogies break down.
And if anyone is concerned about these sort of questions,
you can email my priest, Father David Galaway at south orthodox or landalagymil.com.
Oh man, he just threw his own priest under the bus.
Yes.
Wow.
Wow, I was gonna tell them that they said they hate to
build a father Andrew, but.
Wow.
Okay, so he's a three-headed monster, an appropriate symbol
of the Trinity.
I'm gonna go out, no bill.
No, it's not.
Oh, no.
Oh, man.
I didn't know this was gonna be this much fun tonight.
This is great.
Yeah, no.
What a record.
This is my analogy.
This was not an academic class.
Oh, okay.
Good, good. Yeah, we don't need to we don't need to actually contact your priest and say, excuse me father.
We have some concerns.
Anyway, yeah, you know, here's here's what I say to a lot of that stuff is like, look, use the things that the church has always used.
You know, pray the way the church prays, speak the way the church speaks.
Yes, there sometimes is good space for new
new expressions to try to explain the things we've always believed, new ways of talking about
things we've always believed, and always taught. But particularly when you're talking about
core things like trinitarian dogma, you gotta be careful. You gotta be careful. And I think
the best thing, you know, if people say, look, I just can't swallow this philosophically,
persons one God. Say look you know you know it's not a it's actually
ultimately not a philosophical
It's an experience of prayer.
You know, I was raised, I was raised as an evangelical Protestant who believed in the Trinity.
But I would say that my experience of the Father, Son and Holy Spirit
only really became truly fulsome within the context of Orthodox Christian liturgy and life.
And it wasn't because I altered my views.
I believed the same thing.
But the way that we pray in the Orthodox Church
really brings that home.
So I mean, I know it's just laughing a little bit earlier,
but I'm serious about this.
The actual experience of prayer really does do that.
And I would recommend, so part of the thing here with all of this stuff is that,
The reason people are confused in trying to find analogies is that generally they've received a very bad presentation of the Trinity.
The typical American presentation, regardless of where you are.
Right. The typical thing you get is, well, there's these three persons that are all God, but there's only one God.
Well, yeah, that's confusing. Right? That's not the doctrine of the Trinity.
That's not what's in the
the Nicene Creed. Dr. Trinney is there's one God, the Father, from whom the Son is eternally
generated outside of time, from whom the Holy Spirit perceives outside of time. And so
the Trinity, the triad, is the three persons who share one nature and one will and one energy.
This is straight from St. Gregory of Nusa, the Nicene Creed.
So, I think rather than looking for good analogies, because they all break down horribly, as you
said, we should just go back to basics and just, it's really not as hard to understand
as people have told you it is.
They've just explained it to you badly, and when you asked follow-up questions said, well,
it's impossible to understand, because they don't understand it.
So yeah, if you do, if you go on the Google
right? And you search for monarchical trinity or on the
YouTube's right especially if you find Dr. Bo Branson you can find a lot of
material explaining this it's really something that pretty much any Christian
can understand if it's explained well. All right Daniel thank you very much for
We're calling the Lord of Spear's Podcast tonight.
All right, thank you, fathers.
God bless.
All right, all right.
Moving forward now with Israelite iconography.
Yeah, I hear Dr. Harry in my head,
play it cool, like say, you know the context was
if someone said like, it was literally this context,
what if you get to a parish and you know,
they've got one of these uncannonical icons.
First thing he says, you tear that down,
and he's like, no, no, you play it cool, like same basal.
Yeah.
God bless you, doctor.
over there in Thessaloniki.
Yeah, bless your retirement.
And Daniel.
And he's what among Florida men he is clearly one of the good ones.
The Danimal himself, he said, that's unlike the one who I recently read about who a
through an alligator onto the roof of a building to teach it a lesson.
Wow.
I wonder what the alligator learned from that.
I do not know.
But yeah, it's good times.
All right.
So now is real life iconography?
Yes, yes, is the lights that iconography it turns out?
Yes.
So last time we talked about all the Israelite idolatry that went on, right?
Because of course, despite the fact that they weren't supposed to be doing it, you can't
swing a dead cat in the Old Testament without hitting an Israelite, worshipping an idol.
dead elegantly. That wasn't technically a mixed metaphor, but it wasn't here anyway. So
if we're going to talk about the Zodiacanography, we have to start on the first page of the Bible,
right? Because man and woman are created in the image of God, the Greek translation as the icon
of God in the world.
And we've talked in the show about how the way in particular in Genesis 2 that the creation of
Man did is described as this sort of inversion of the way in which an idol was installed at the end of the
dedication of a pagan temple. So rather than this image being crafted of the God and then a ritual
taking place.
to place the Spirit, to open its nostrils and place the Spirit of the God within the idol
so that it could be manipulated and worshiped through it.
God creates humanity in his image and he breathes life.
He breathes his Spirit into the human person to make it his living image, to act on his
behalf and through which for him.
to act in his creation. So it is an exact inversion and reversal of the idle making that went
on in the construction of pagan temples and in the pagan world. So icon making here at the
beginning of Genesis is the inversion, the opposite, the antithesis of idle making.
Yeah, a review, really.
Yes.
Yeah.
And that means there is a distinction between idolatry and iconography from the first page of the Scriptures.
A distinction made by God himself.
Yes.
These two things are distinguished at the very beginning of Scripture.
Right.
They're not on a continuum, they're not the same thing.
The one is the opposite of the other.
Right, these two things stand up host.
And so, when we get a little later on in the Torah, and we get to the point that the
tabernacle is being designed and being built, there are cherubim all over the place.
cherimum sewn into the effectively the walls of the tabernacle.
There are a cherubim in the most holy place,
around where the Ark of the Covenant
that we'll talk about in a minute is going to be.
And this is because this iconography,
right, this is iconography of the divine counsel,
the angelic being surrounding the throne of God
because the cherubim inside the holy place
are the ones that form the throne of God.
Now are the gigantic turbums.
statues are those in the tabernacle or do you have to wait to the temple to get those?
Well they get more gigantic of the temple, but those are the ones I'm referring to.
Yeah, okay.
Right. In the holy place, this represents the throne of God, right, at the high place.
Right. We seated upon the chairman. So this is iconography of the divine council surrounding him.
Right. And
And this is not just O a nice decoration or
Oh, theologically significant, because we go, oh, this is representing that place.
So the Mussolian place is the throne of God on an intellectual level.
But Hebrews eight verse five points out that the tabernacle itself is a whole is an icon
of the heavenly sanctuary.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
The place of the throne and presence of God into which Moses entered when he was on top
Mount Sinai.
So the entire structure, this is not a structure with some iconography in it.
The entire structure is an icon.
Its entire purpose is to be an icon to allow for ritual participation in heavenly worship.
That is the whole purpose and function of the tabernacle.
If you take away a concept of iconography, the tabernacle doesn't make sense of it.
anymore. This is its primary function, of its whole design, which chapters and chapters
and chapters are spent on in Exodus. This design. And one of the places where in the whole
construction of the tabernacle that this distinction between iconography and idolatry becomes
most pointed is in the construction of the arch.
the covenant itself. Yeah, which is great example. Which is going to go into the most holy place,
which is going to be the footstool, right, at the foot of God's throne, right, between those
those cherubim, right. And on top of the ark, on the cover, right, and see atonement episodes for
why it's just the cover. Mercy seat.
Yes.
Of lid.
They're commanded to make two literal graven images on it.
Two literal graven images of things in the heavens above.
Yeah.
By God, like, this is not a Moses idea.
This is God.
This isn't Moses giving in.
Like, hey, we got a lot of former pagans here.
God, can we throw them a bone?
Can we incorporate some of their practices?
Hahaha.
not to bring up Pachamama. Sorry. Sorry.
Oh, um, shots fired.
Right. But, but, but the way the Ark of the Coventry is designed, like so many things in
the tabernacle, we've talked about these before. Right. Um, how all of all of these things, the imagery,
all of these things, the furniture are things that have
I'm gonna wrap it up.
relevance to what a pagan would be used to, but they've been changed. Right. So we've talked before about how instead of
the priests having to come in and feed
the God, right, there is the table of the showbred
from which God feeds his priests.
Right. So these things are these pagan things are taken and inverted and changed to make a point. Yeah, it's always flipped
over turned around reverse to whatever.
Yeah.
So the Egyptian equivalent of the Ark of the Covenant,
so the Ark of the Covenant does follow an Egyptian design.
But in that Egyptian design,
they say it's not a brand new unique thing.
Right.
And that Egyptians that are these barks,
they were often put on boats,
sailed up in another Nile, and this kind of thing.
and on these marks on the lid.
there would be these two winged goddesses, usually ISIS and nephus, on either side,
extending their wings over those wings we're sheltering in the center and idol of a god.
Yep, and sacrifice would be offered to that idol. Right. Right. And so in this Egyptian
version we have here a good pagan example we have an
It's used for idolatry there at the center, and then it is surrounded by religious iconography.
Right? Just like if you walked into an Egyptian pagan temple,
there's an idol there at the center of the God, but there's all kinds of religious iconography painted on the walls. Right?
So, I beg your name,
when you look at the Ark of the Covenant, the one God commands them to build, you have these two-wing cherubim
that aren't given names because there are
not to be treated as other gods, right? And then in the center between their wings,
overshadowed by their wings, you have nothing. Nothing. Yeah. Right? So you have the iconography
without the idol. Right? The distinction between the Ark of the Covenant and its pagan equivalent
is precisely the removal of the idol.
Two different things, right? Two different things, iconography and idols. And by the way, just
because this is a bug bear that comes up every so often, they did not think God lived
inside the ark of the covenant. The ark of the covenant was never a box with God in
it. Yeah. Our God is in heaven and on earth. He does it. He does it. It was the footstool
of his throne.
Right.
it's the place. If you're going to approach God, the great king of creation, you come up to his
footstool and you bow and you make reverence there to speak to them. So the Ark of the Covenant is
the place where it's the point of contact, right, is the point of contact between God and our world.
Right, is the point.
Contact is where on the day of atonement every year, right? Remember Yahweh the God of Israel appeared above the Ark of the Covenant meaning
With his feet on it his throne appeared right he appeared right there
And so yeah, that's he's not inside it
He's not inside
Now interestingly
Right
You know?
All this we just discussed about the tabernacle and the arc of the covenant here in Exodus,
coming as it does right after the 10 commandments and the second commandment about not making
a grave image and bound down to it and serving it.
Funnily enough, there's no distinction made here between iconography and idolatry.
Yeah, because people know.
Yeah, they're still sort of...
explanation or clause. There's no place where Moses says like okay okay guys
remember that thing I said about not making a great move image of everything
and anything in heaven and then I just told you now to make the the cherubim on
the ark. Okay here's how that all works right. It's okay in this case because God
said so or well it's okay but guys just don't go too far with the
veneration thing and do an idolatry right. Doesn't do that. Doesn't disambiguate
it. Just like seeing it, the affidation doesn't disambiguate it.
that we talked about last time. Right?
There's a why?
Why? Who have you? He's modern readers. We ask we look at that. We say like that looks like a contradiction
Well, it means for the Bronze Age people who received it
The Iron Age people who read it over and over again and meditated upon it for their entire lives
It was a distinction that didn't need to be made
They understood it.
They got it. They knew what iconography was and they knew what an idol was. Yeah.
Because there are people worshiping idols. They are surrounded by iconography of various
kinds. Everybody knew these were two different things. They didn't think they were related
in any way. Right? It's like I don't have to go and present you an argument as to why
chalk and cheese are two different things. Right? If I said chalk and cheese are just...
like you look at me like I'm a nut, right? For someone to really be confused about whether
chalk and cheese are the same thing, they'd have to either have never seen cheese or never
seen chalk, right? And that's kind of why we now have to make these distinctions.
Yeah, because people don't know what idolatry is. They didn't ever see it. People these days
haven't seen real literal idolatry.
talked about other kinds of idolatry last time.
Metaphorical idolatry.
That we've certainly seen.
But the real literal stuff, most of us have never seen.
Right, and that's a good thing.
I don't recommend going and attending pagan rituals
throughout idols.
But yeah, we don't really know what it is.
Now suddenly imagining someone going up
to some pagan temple, hey, so I heard about this
on this podcast.
Let's see.
Yeah, y'all are doing in there.
Yeah, well, most of the time those are going to be revived.
The rest of the world is going to be those revived paganism stuff, which also is the same
thing.
Right.
It's very Protestant paganism.
You know, where they're definitely not sacrificing any animals because half the members
are vegan.
So, that's true.
Yeah.
But yeah, so for people who are a-
immersed in this world.
It was just apparent to them that these are different things.
And that includes everyone from the original
hears of the Torah all the way up through the church
fathers.
Right.
They knew what went on in pagan temples
in terms of idolatry.
They understood pagan religious iconography,
and they understood Jewish and Christian iconography.
Yeah.
They didn't think they were the same thing.
Right? They understood. These are just two different things.
So a sort of case study of this.
And this is a good case study because it's an example of iconography and example of
idolatry that involve the same physical object.
Yeah.
Right?
In the context of these relights in their history.
So the first one of the
is from everybody's favorite book of the Bible numbers. Yeah. Yeah. Probably the most well-known
story of numbers because Christ Himself refers to it in St. John's Gospel. Indeed. About the
Bronze Surfer. Yeah. Okay. So this is from Numbers chapter 21, starting with verse 4 and going through
verse 9. From Mount Hore, they set out by the way to the Red Sea to go around the land of Edom,
and the people became impatient on the way.
And the
The people spoke against God and against Moses.
Why have you brought us up out of Egypt to die in the wilderness?
There is no food and no water and we loathe this worthless food, then the Lord sent fiery
serpents among the people and they bit the people so that many people of Israel died.
And the people came to Moses and said, we have sinned for we have spoken against the Lord
and against you.
Pray to the Lord that He take away the serpents from us.
So Moses prayed for the people.
And the Lord said to Moses,
make a fiery serpent and set it on a pole, and everyone who is bitten when he sees it
shall live. So Moses made a bronze serpent and set it on a pole. And if a serpent bit anyone,
he would look at the bronze serpent and live. So that's use, correct use, doing the thing that God
I said to do with this icon of fiery serpent everybody.
Seraph.
Yeah.
Right. And so, right, God again tells them to make a grave in image. Right. But how is it being used?
Right. It's being used as an instrument through which God heals people.
Yeah. Notice the direction of the action, right? From back in Genesis.
What makes Adam different than an idol? Right. Adam is there to cooperate with God so that God
That can work.
through him in creation. So this is God working healings through this image that he commanded
them to make. That's the direction of the actions from God to people through image.
Later on, they held onto this snake and centuries later something else happens in second kings
or fourth kingdoms.
Yeah. Chapter 18, verses 1 through 4.
In the third year of Hosea, son of Ilah, king of Israel, Hezekiah, the son of Ahaz,
king of Judah, began to reign.
He was 25 years old when he began to reign, and he reigns 29 years in Jerusalem.
His mother's name was Abbi, the daughter of Zechariah.
And he did what was right in the eyes of the Lord, according to all the David's father
had done.
He removed the high places and broke the pillars and cut down the Ashrah, and he broke
in pieces the brush.
Serpent that Moses had made for until those days the people of Israel had made offerings to it. It was called
Nahushtan
So same object
Being treated in a very different way right so we're told here the Israelites are making offerings to it
Yeah, that's and calling it yeah, and they gave it a name notice
Yeah, whooshtan which means the great serpent
And
Right. So now taking this, they're treating it as the embodiment of this great serpent,
and they're going and making sacrifices to the great serpent through it. So the action is going
from humans toward a spirit that is not God, right, through the idol, which they believe embodies
that spirit, right? And therefore it has to be destroyed, right? So these are two varied
different types of actions.
They are opposite actions.
Just like iconography and idolatry
are opposites at the beginning of Genesis.
They're opposites here.
The action is moving in either direction.
You can take one object and use it in very different ways.
One can be a good and holy way
and the other can be a dark evil sinful way.
Yes.
Right?
And that doesn't mean that doesn't mean...
you know, the Puritan argument, therefore we get rid of all of the object. Yeah. So that no one can do the bad thing with it. Yeah. Right. Yeah. You know, everybody talks about the Pharisees trying to build a fence around the law.
It's a Puritan's who tried to build a fence around the law. Right. No dancing because of what it might lead to. Right.
I can't touch alcohol because someone might get
drunk. Yeah. Right. These are not good arguments. These are the kind of rules that St. Paul
refers to when he talks about rules that say do not taste, do not touch. Yeah. Right.
And how those are people to be avoided. So I was going to say so speaking of flaming
serpents. We actually have a caller and I think this is probably someone who is known to
Are they in the labing circuit?
I don't know.
We'll find out in a second and what are you doing on the phone, Sarah?
We have jewels from Louisiana. Oh boy.
Jules.
I'm not bad. Welcome. I mean, you know, isn't he your priest? Couldn't you just talk to him at church? Why are you calling the podcast shows?
It's the hubris of thinking that this question is gonna enlighten the general public.
No, no, this is not an enlightening
I'm just sitting in my apartment and I have a question.
Oh, you're sad and lonely.
Okay, fair enough.
Talk to us.
We're listening.
Okay.
My question is, in a lot of iconography,
especially with like St. George, he's playing the dragon
and way back in a long time,
about dragons basically being terrorists.
You know, but also in all the Byzantine I
You say I said right
Okay, I'm being encouraging. Go ahead. Go ahead
Thank you. I appreciate that and all the Byzantine iconography. I've seen of the Seraphim
It always depicts them sort of with a human head with wings around them. Yeah, so
What distinction other than one's an angel and one's a demon?
like, like what was the way we gained from the differences of those
detections?
Yeah, so I mean, number one, I'm going to say I think you need to get out a little
bit more and I'm not commenting on your social life tools. I have no idea what
that's like. But the reason I say that is because I have seen iconostasis with
dragons incorporated into them. And they're not being depicted like being
defeated by
saints or angels or whatever. They are in honorable places. Bishop staff. Yeah, yeah, they go on
the Bishop staff. You've got serpents in the Bishop staff as well. So, so it's not that the bad
guy's always appear in one way and this in good guys always appear another way. It's just that
what happened is there's this other way of depicting Seraphim developed largely because of this
association of the serpent with in Genesis 3, you know, but still the serpent.
untied imagery persists. You know, so how do you know the difference? It's really about context.
If you see, say, George stabbing it, that's a bad one.
If you see it on a kind of stasis or on investments or on the bishop's staff, that's a good one.
You know, the context makes it clear. Also, the other depiction,
and four of the wings are covering their body.
Oh, yeah.
Sorry.
I mean, they could have a serpentine body.
Okay, this humble, I think more of a yeah.
Yeah.
So okay.
All right.
Does that answer your question, Jules from Louisiana?
That is that is the fish answer my question.
It's more about what are not there's a sword going through
it or spear going through it than scales.
I mean, again, it's really yeah, it's about context.
What's happening in this picture?
Okay.
You know, all right.
Yeah.
All right, Joy Cleveland.
Enjoy Cleveland.
Thank you very much, tools.
All right.
Yes.
So yeah, we were saying the difference between, you know,
differences in the actions, whether something that we can see just with
the, just with the serpent.
Yeah.
And then there's not to go with the Puritans and get rid of images, right?
Like,
Well, I see I know Puritan types who take it this far where they won't even...
have a cross in their church because somebody might decide to worship it somehow.
Sneak up to it, offer some sacrifices. Yeah, I mean, I don't even know exactly how that would work,
but I know. I know. But, you know, like I'm thinking, I'm thinking more of like in the, in the first
bread and fresher mummy movie right there's the scene with the guy where the
mummy's coming at him and so he
He pulls this cross on a chain out of his shirt and like holds it up.
And the mummy doesn't stop coming.
So he like pulls out a crescent moon and then he pulls out a star of David and then he
pulls out like he's got it like to cover all of his bases, right?
But you'll find one that will ward off the mummy, right?
So it's like sure, there could be a guy like that who's not a Christian even and is just
using the cross as a magic amulet or something, right?
That doesn't mean...
should stop wearing crosses. Yeah. Right. Like, yeah. You know, it's that old, it's that old Latin phrase,
a boost is non-tolate-usom. I'm sure I'm just pronouncing it, sorry, Latin teachers, but you know,
the abuse of something does not negate the use. Right. Right. Right. And so, and, you know, if this
This isn't just again, us.
arguing, right? There's nothing in second Kings to indicate, oh man, God made a big mistake
when he had Moses make that serpent because it led all those people into idolatry. Yeah.
Right? There's not a whiff of that in the Hebrew Scriptures. Right? The blame here is
entirely on the people for what they did. Right? So yeah. And so we find because this distinction
is in
drained throughout iconography's one thing that we do,
and idolatries this other thing that we shouldn't do,
but a lot of us do within Israel, right?
And then Judah, it's not surprising that when we excavate
the earliest synagogues we found,
they're full of iconography.
There are tons of mosaics.
We have piles.
piles is the wrong word to use. We have a number of first century synagogue ruins, piles
of ruins just did sound right. From the first century because the Romans went around
destroying them in Galilee. Right? And so we have, and a lot of them, we have the floors.
Right? And the mosaics and the floors that have the zodiacs we talked about in our episode
about astrology.
You have.
One of my favorite episodes of all time actually.
If you do say so yourself.
I do.
Yeah.
You're telling me the other day how you thought you were
particularly ingenious and on point during that episode.
And besides just the zodiacs, sacred maps,
right, meaning maps of sacred geography, where you have sort of spiritual
locations and material locations as we
would call them sort of mixed together in these
mappings and of course...
just representative representations of biblical figures and biblical narratives. I can
ography of Moses. I canography of David. Jonah, I mean I could just go to the Samuel. Yeah.
And scenes from biblical narratives, right, being depicted iconographically, right? And then
of course in synagogues, post-exiluc synagogues, you have the development of Moses' seat,
right? The seat of Moses, which
when there's no one actually sitting in it with teaching authority,
is itself serving a kind of iconographic function
of representing the authority of the Torah within the community,
as a physical depiction.
And so there's kind of within Jewish iconography,
as we're coming to the time of Christ.
And as I said,
We know this from these Galilee and synagogues. These are the synagogues that we read in the
Gospels about Christ going and preaching in them. Yeah, he would have been standing in
a big mosaics of the zodiac. Right.
Standing in the midst of all this iconography. Right. And there really are kind of two main
categories we could say?
Or types?
And those are sort of religious depictions being specifically scriptural depictions really in this case of persons and events
from the scriptures
and then cosmic depictions
Right, so depictions of the heavenly realms or cosmic geography
These kind of things right things structured to show like even the zodiacs are structured to give an image of the night sky
which is the heavens, right, which they...
believed was a means God used to communicate with us.
So we can kind of talk about those two broad categories.
And they seem to have come into, because of course the iconography we talked about in the
tabernacle gets adapted in the temple.
But the synagogue iconography, which is somewhat different in the ways we just described,
Seems to have been...
developed out of the decoration of various shrines and gravesites, right, where the relics
of prophets and saints were, Jewish prophets and saints. In the post-exilic period,
those are the first places where we start finding these kind of things and then they kind of
flower within the synagogues. Where you go to, you know, the gravesite of the prophet Jonah,
Right, unfortunately recently destroyed by ISIS.
And there are, right, I cut a graphic depictions of Jonah and, you know, him being swallowed
by a fish and, right, these sort of things, right?
Yes, I know, Leviathan.
But these scenes from his life, him, you know, preaching at the overthrow of Nineveh, right?
We find those depictions there, right, at the tombs of the prophets.
Christ even references this at one point when he talks about
how the Pharisees adorn the tombs of the prophets. These are the kind of
adornments that were on the tombs that were on the tombs of the prophets.
And we never see Jesus saying that there's a problem with this anywhere, even
though it's all around him, and going on in the synagogues. He never expresses a
problem with synagogue worship, right? Says this, though this stuff's bogus, he
should really be doing tempo stuff and that's
it, right? We never see that, right? And this is why there are the early Christians just
take over synagogue worship as Christian worship, right? Follow the same pattern.
But he also never says anything negative about decorating the shrines or by the way,
going to the shrines and the relics of Jewish saints to pray, never says anything negative about
that. He makes a contrast. Like he says, you know, you adorn the tombs that profits,
That's right but...
you, you know, but your behavior is garbage, which the reason why that's a contrast is because
it's okay and good to adorn the tombs the props. Yeah, it's good. Yeah, yeah. Yeah.
But you aren't like them. Yeah. That's, and in fact, your forefathers hated them.
And it's okay, since it killed them and put them in those tombs.
Yeah, so that seems to be sort of the direct line.
So to finish up here, talking about Israelite iconography, I want to point to a particular
story in the life of Christ that's largely misunderstood, I think.
Yeah, and you have to follow closely here, folks, because this is probably a little different
than people are used to thinking about the passage we're about to read.
Well, and it's because partially because of how it appears.
in translation partly because of just a history of interpretation that really doesn't make sense if
you think about it for two seconds. And partially because of a lack of understanding of
this principle of iconography. And this is when in St. Matthew's Gospel, Christ gets asked by
the Pharisees about paying taxes to Caesar. Yeah. Okay. So this is Matthew chapter 22. I'm going to read
versus 15 through 22. Then the Pharisees went and plotted.
how to entangle him in his words. And they said their disciples to him, along with the
Herodians saying, Teacher, we know that you are true and teach the way of God truthfully,
and you do not care about anyone's opinion for you are not swayed by appearances, tell
us then what you think. Is it lawful to pay taxes to Caesar or not? But Jesus, aware
of their malice, said, Why put me to the test you hypocrites? Show me the coin for the tax.
they brought him a
scenarios. And Jesus said to them, whose likeness and inscription is this? They said Caesars.
Then he said to them, therefore, render to Caesar the things that are Caesars and
to God the things that are gods. When they heard it, they marveled and they left him and went away.
So the weird thing is, is like a lot of people come away from this with the idea of Jesus
saying yeah you should pay your taxes.
you know, you should pay your taxes.
And then it says, and they marveled, like,
whoa, he said, pay your taxes.
Right.
And so the whole point here is that they're trying,
they're trying to pull something by asking this question.
They're trying to entangle him in his words, right?
They're plotting against him.
Yes.
And so this is a setup question, right?
the setup is if Jesus says, yeah, pay your taxes.
then the disciples of the Pharisees and the Herodians, who are up to this, could say,
hey, look, this guy's a Roman collaborator.
Right.
He's on the side of the Romans.
He's no good.
Right, and get all the people who hate the Romans for a variety of reasons that are obvious if you know Roman history.
Well, we'll all get riled up against Jesus.
And if he says, no, you shouldn't pay your taxes, then they can run to the Romans and say,
Hey, this guy's out there.
They're getting big crowds together telling them not to pay their taxes.
Right.
So this is the trap.
This is how they're trying to entangle him.
Right.
So if Jesus' answer was just, yeah, you should pay your taxes.
Why would they marvel and be amazed?
Yeah, they'd be like, gotcha.
Yeah.
Ha ha.
Go get the local Centurion.
Right.
Right, the Pharisees turning Jesus over the Romans.
would be a scandal, but the Herodians didn't care.
That's their all collaborators.
Right, so we're clearly misunderstanding if we think that the answer that Jesus gives.
And so part of this is the way, verse 20 in particular, is translated in English.
That's where Jesus says to them, whose as it was in English, likeness and inscription
is this?
The word that's used for likeness there is.
icon. So it's literally the word icon. Whose icon is this? Whose image is this? Right? And so he
Christ is throwing this back at them. Right? Because there's a play out words here. Right? So on one
level. Okay, yeah, that's a picture of Caesar.
Right? That's a picture of Caesar. That Caesar's image on the coin. Caesar's icon. Right.
But whose icon is Caesar? Caesar is a man. And therefore, as we said earlier, he is the icon of God, an icon of God. Right.
And that's why Christ follows it up by saying,
render to Caesar the thing-
that are Caesars and to God the things that are gods.
Right?
Sure.
Caesar minted this coin.
Right?
If he wants a back, give it back to him.
But what belongs to God?
Yeah, this coin, everything else.
Everything including Caesar and the coin.
Right?
Yeah, and you can't...
So sure.
You know, you can't use this coin like if you're in the temple.
because it's got this Caesar being a God of the Romans, it's got a false God on it. Right, right.
So it was considered. Yeah, yeah. So the idea here is give Caesar back his coin, give God everything
and they're like, okay, yeah, he got us back, right? We can't turn that around on him, right?
But, as you mentioned, this is a coin that...
couldn't be used in the temple because of the image of Caesar on it.
That's why there's money changes out front.
There's money changes in the temple because they had separate
coins that was used internally
in the temple treasury.
And so
Christ's answer here is deliberately
playing on
this distinction between idle and icon
because Caesar himself is an...
idol. Right. He's an idol because they believe he's in an embodiment of the God. And they offer
sacrifice to him. They offer sacrifice to him. Right. And to the state. Right. That's an idol. Right.
And Christ is pointing out by making this distinction that actually know he's called to serve as an icon.
Yep. Because everything including him belongs to God.
indeed. So in a few minutes we're going to take a break but we actually do
a caller that I thought we would talk to before we take our next break. And that is James
calling from Nevada. So James from out there in the deserts of Western, Western United States
welcomed Laura Spears podcast. Thank you. It's an honor to be here a long time listener first time
caller. Well, you know, the funny thing is on our very first episode, we had someone say that
we're very first episode. And I kind of wanted it at the time like is someone going to still say
that like years from now and here
We are three years later and it's you.
So.
I will tell you that people who live here will say it's pronounced Nevada.
And Nevada, but not Nevada.
Camino Camino.
Yeah.
Well, you know, for a long time, I was pronouncing the town that Father Stephen
and lived in as Lafayette because that's the more kind of French way of saying it.
But they say it Lafayette.
And he corrected me.
So if you listen to the early episodes, you can hear me say Lafayette.
So I'm willing to be corrected and say Nevada.
Okay.
Wonderful. Well thanks, thanks so much for having me. So I really appreciated the earlier
illustration of the bronze serpent, you know, it's right usage and it's wrong usage. And
as a former Protestant, my experience in orthodoxy has been, you know, there's always the Protestant
objections or that outsider.
way of thinking where certain objections might come up.
And so in regards to, I think kind of a parallel modern example
that is actually a good friend of mine.
He was recently baptized of venerios.
And as I'm sure you're well aware, there's a practice of praying to state
venerios when you lost something, when you do find it, then bringing,
I forget what it's called, the obesity bringing, right?
you bake cakes and you...
bring it as sort of this offering.
So as an orthodox Christian, I know this isn't a form of idolatry,
but I could see a lot of outsider non-orthodox people
saying, well, wait a second.
This is you praying to somebody else in God.
And then when you getting in a sense, your answer,
now you're offering this hospitality.
This person now, this is an offering.
How is this non- idolatry?
You kind of like they might point to the illustration
how
the wrong usage of the bronze circuit.
So I would love to hear your response
on how you would counter that way of thinking to those.
So please do enlighten me
and anyone else who may think that as well.
Yeah, so this thing is called a fanuropita.
That's the cake, the St. Fenerios cake.
Right, so I mean, we've talked a bunch of times
about asking the saints.
their help. So we probably don't need to kind of roll through that again. But yeah, yeah.
But yeah, the part that probably might make people go wait a minute, especially if they've
been listening to this podcast, wait a minute, they're putting food in front of that icon.
What's going on here, buddy? Right? So there's a lot of important dissimilarities. One really
important dissimilarity.
is that in idolatry, the offerings are made in order to get the result that you want.
And if you make the offerings in the correct way, then you're guaranteed the result.
So it's a kind of religious technology.
So that's one distinction.
With the funeropeita, it's blessed as a way of saying thank you to something that has all
already been reached.
received. Right? So there was simply a request made and the answer could be new. You know,
and you know, the tradition for those who have never heard of this is St. Funurios who
himself was a sort of lost saint like he was forgotten by the church. And then his icon
was discovered in Rhodes and he appeared to the, I think it was a bishop that discovered
the icon and they didn't really know anything about his life other than the images that were
on the icon.
because it was what they call a life icon, which has sort of scenes from the life.
And so apparently at the time, St. Furnerio said to him,
if someone's, because I was lost, if someone loses something, I will help them find it,
but in exchange I'm going to ask them to say a prayer for my mother
and to offer this cake as a memorial as part of that.
So I mean, you know, we have other...
memorial food, right? We have Kulivah that we offer in the church when we pray for the departed,
which is so sort of fundamentally what the Fond de Ropata is. It's food that's blessed as part
of a memorial for someone. But importantly, it is not brought in a procession. It is not divided up
between the priests and the people. It is not placed on an altar. It is not offered up to a spirit
it as to a God. It is, I mean, it goes on and on.
think about all the things that go into sacrificial ritual,
both pagan sacrificial ritual and Christian Eucharist, right?
Has all those things that I just mentioned in common?
Fonder Opita has the practice of blessing
of Fonder Opita doesn't have any of that in common.
I mean, it has way more in common with happy birthday.
Here is a cake that we have made to celebrate you
and to be thankful for all that you are.
and we're gonna pray over it.
and blessed and divided up amongst everybody here.
Like has way more in common with birthday cake.
You know?
So just because the piece of food is put in front of an image
doesn't make it a sacrifice.
There's a whole set of ritual that goes along with it,
that goes along with sacrifice
that is simply not there in the tradition
of the Fanny Rope.
Even like I, when I was much younger
in the Orthodox church, I knew someone in my parish,
not the person I'm in now is
This is a long, long time ago, who, I mean, God lover, this woman must have lost her
keys every single day and got seen for New New Year's to help her find it or whatever,
because like she was bringing fun and open to the church.
It seemed like once a week, almost sometimes.
And I was like, oh, I guess she lost something again.
You know, get it one of those things where you whistle and your keys beep at you.
I don't know.
But even then, even like when it's sort of almost kind of semi-obsessive like that, it's
still not idolatry.
It's still not.
You
Yeah, so so I guess my follow up would be then you're telling me that celebrating birthdays is not a pagan ritual
It's been so how you do it. Sorry watch tower Bible and tracks aside. Yeah, exactly
Sorry Jehovah's Witnesses
No, no, it's I mean
Yeah, I mean we celebrate the birthday of the Lord. That's right. So that was that was just more
I'm going to slide comment but that I hear you both disambiguing that so I I appreciate that that clarification so
So thanks for thanks for that and for all that you guys do so huge fan of what you guys do and it's been a huge part of
My journey through orthodoxy as well. So thank you. Thank God. Please. Please remember us in your prayers
Yes, happily, too
Alright, thank you James from Nevada. Alright Nevada Nevada
before the break, before the, go ahead, Father.
And related to that.
So imagine somebody gets a cancer diagnosis.
And it's not a good one.
And so they ask a group of their friends to pray for them.
And over the next months,
while they're getting treatment,
all their friends are praying for them.
And then at the end of the treatment,
They find out they've gone into rem-
mission. And so they throw up party and they invite all those people who are
praying for them over and they say, thank you so much for praying for me. It's so
wonderful what God has done in healing me. And we've set out this big spread so
everybody eaten in joy, right? Now imagine thinking that's idolatry because
That's kind of what I hear when a Protestant asked that kind of question.
about St. Fenureus because there's an underlying assumption there that the saints, these actual
Christian people who actually lived, who continue to live in Christ and who are still part of
our church community, and we're part of theirs, are somehow more comparable to pagan gods than to
our fellow Christians, which is what they actually are.
Right?
The question presupposes that St. Fenurious is some kind of pagan God.
It's not arguing it.
It's presupposing it.
Because if this person is like my Christian uncle, who I asked to pray for me for something
and then invite him to eat with me, to give thanks to God that the prayers were answered,
No one in there right?
No.
would call that idolatry. Right? So this is about a weird pathology that's been
ground into a lot of our Protestant friends to think of Christians from former
past generations of the Church as somehow pagan, or as somehow, right, their
spirit, their spirit.
They're the spirits of the righteous made perfect in Christ.
They're not demonic.
Right.
It's kind of the all-like.
Yeah.
That's nuts.
Right.
Yeah.
Yep.
All right.
That said, we're going to take our second and final break and we'll be right back
with the third half of the Lord of Spirits podcast.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment.
Make your calls on the next part of the Lord.
of spirits. Give them a call at 855-237-2346. That's 855-AF Radio.
It's easy to shy away from talk about the goodness of creation,
as if that implicates a consumer of supports through the world or some kind of hiddenism.
But when the early Christians discussed the goodness of creation, they meant that the world
has a purpose, and that the earth is a real theophany of heaven the order.
I'm Robin Phillips, and my recent book, Rediscovering the Goodness of Creation, walks
through God's plan for the earth.
Through the teaching of Scripture and the saints, we discover that God's purpose for the world
is not to destroy it, nor for us to spend eternity disembodied in heaven.
our God plans to one day resurrect the earth so we can experience the world as we were
meant to.
This has implications for how we live today, including how we work, raise our families,
appreciate art, approach marriage and work with technology.
We're discovering the goodness of creation is available at store.nchettevade.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Hey everybody, welcome back.
It is the third half of Laura Spirits' podcast.
That commercial will prove to be apropos by the end of this half.
It's true.
It's true, eerily appropriate.
Nice choice, Smontras Goodchurty,
of that commercial there.
You know, it's funny in our YouTube stream,
someone commented in the chat,
third half question mark,
and I'm like, oh, he must be new.
Yeah, you're new.
Welcome.
There was once,
there was once,
and only once so far, a fourth half.
That's true. That's true.
There was a fourth half.
That was a double, double show.
We were firing on all cylinders.
Dude, dude. Alright, so in the first half,
we talked about.
Pagan iconography. Second half, Jewish is relied, I should say, is relied iconography.
Sorry, Jewish is just a subset of Israelite.
Israelite iconography. And now here in Act 3, finally, Christian iconography.
So, yeah, this just pops out of nowhere, just suddenly invented by some kind of idolatrising
fourth century Christians in Syria, maybe. Yes, clearly. Oh, no, the opposite of that. No.
So, yeah.
There's precedent.
So, literally, what we find is the earliest Christians, as with so many things, just take
over what's being done in Second Temple Jewish communities and specifically synagogues
and continue it, but in a Christian context.
Keep doing it.
So you continue to have...
the same types of iconography that you had in synagogues in Christian churches, obviously
with the person of Jesus Christ taking a sort of supreme prominence in that iconography.
But also his mother prominently being featured, St. John the Forerunner, St. Peter and Paul,
figures right because we have more scriptures now.
Right. And so we start to see other figures appearing in the iconography, but the iconography is continued and and
those
Figures and events from the Hebrew Scriptures don't go away either. They're just added to yeah, right the story continues. Yeah
And so
That yeah function just continues as churches start to be constructed and decorated they follow the same pattern of the tabernacle as forming this
This is the end of the video.
iconographic function themselves as a space, reproducing the divine council, the heavenly
throne room, the presence of God, which is being entered into.
And so the fundamental problem that faces the iconoclast, ancient or modern, although
So at least the ancient one didn't have archaeology, etc.
So, this becomes an even more pointed problem for the modern iconoclast
is that the modern iconoclast has to argue that Christianity in particular
was iconoclastic.
They have to argue that Christians came along and removed Jewish iconography.
Yeah, it's said, no, no icons. We're Christians now.
Right? For some reason. Right? The Christianity's iconoclast over iconoclastic over against
Judaism, which makes no sense in light of the incarnation, in light of our understanding
of the incarnation. If anything based on the incarnation, you would expect Christianity
you be less iconoclastic. Yes. More icons, right?
I got I got I could be more prominent or more important right and
This is this is the line of argument that all of the church fathers of the
Economic Classic period who are arguing against iconic lesbians make they point to
the incarnation
Right they point to the incarnation they point to the matter that made up Christ's body
Right?
the matter that made up the cross on which he was crucified.
The physical matter, the physicality of the incarnation of our salvation, right, Christ's
human mother, who is a human person.
That's what they point to, right?
Because of anything, again, Christianity would be less iconoclastic.
So if you can frame an argument that while Second Temple Judaism was fine with iconography
Thank you.
Christianity for some reason was iconoclastic.
If you can find a theological way to frame that argument,
I'd love to hear it,
because I've never heard anyone even attempt it.
Modern iconoclastic.
No, no.
Their only argument is an argument from silence,
a series of arguments from silence.
We don't have evidence yet.
We haven't dug anything up yet.
We haven't, right?
There's not a lot of comments about it.
in this or that church father, right?
Like the argument we mentioned last time, right?
St. Athanasius doesn't mention it.
These are all just a series of arguments from silence.
To make the iconic classic point, with the knowledge
of history that we have, the archeology we have,
you have to make a theological argument that, based
on the theology of the New Testament,
Early Christians became iconoclastic over against
the Judaism of the time.
Yeah, that it was a reform movement effectively.
When it came to iconography, yeah.
Yeah.
And like I said, I'd love to hear it because I don't think you've got a snowball's chance
and you know where of making that argument.
Yeah.
And I'm going to talk now about some of the actual real things that have been done.
Archaeology.
Prove that this is true.
But it's important to see what are the things that assumes.
The work.
We talked about ancient iconoclas, contemporary iconoclas.
You got the mid-range people.
You got your John Calvin's.
You look at John Calvin's arguments against iconography.
You could see where they just went wrong.
He says there was absolutely no iconography before 580.
Sorry.
There was.
We know now for a fact.
You can't make that argument.
Yeah, right.
like we literally have proof that that's not true, right?
But, hey, arguments from silence, right?
They never get you into trouble.
But also, right?
But also, they were based on this assumption
and we've talked about this a lot on the show,
that people made in the early modern period
and some people even make to this day
that the Judaism at the local synagogue, right?
Even if it's a reform synagogue, frankly, the Judaism and the local synagogue is identical
to what was going on in the Second Temple period, which it's not.
Jewish iconoclasm, the Jewish by and large rejection of images was a reaction against
Christian iconography.
use of iconography. There was a reform movement within
rabbinic Judaism in the post-Christian period that was iconoclastic. But Calvin didn't know that.
Right? John Calvin thought, oh, Jewish people don't use iconography, don't have iconography.
So at the time of Christ, they didn't have iconography. Christian started doing it at some point.
Yeah, as far as he knew that was.
true, but we now know it's not true, that the opposite is true, that the synagogues
at the time of Christ were full of iconography. And we're full of iconography for some time
afterward, like centuries afterward. Right. And that movement happened over there on the
rabbinic Jewish side, not on the Christian side. Right. The Christian side is in continuity
with that. So Christians didn't start using iconography ever. They were...
always using it. That's why here and there, as you pick through some of whom are legitimately
fathers and some of whom are definitely not, some of whom are just early Christian writers,
as you pick through people in the early centuries, you here and there find someone who's
kind of iconoclastic in some sense. Right? Those are the outliers.
The people who don't comment on it are surrounded by it.
Yeah, there's not another there's not an argument being made for it because
It's not a controversial question.
Yes.
You know?
Yeah. It's like, it's like, you know,
Well, when was the last time that your Baptist church someone actually argued for using a hymnol?
You know, like it's not argued for. It's just the thing that everybody does.
Right. And let's say, let's say hymnoles were abolished at some point.
Good favor of overhead projectors or PowerPoint, right?
Right. And then somebody might come
many years later, right?
And be like, oh, well, this person in the 19th or 20th century
doesn't say anything about hymnals,
so they must not have had them.
Yeah.
And then the problem is, then you dig one up.
Which is what happens, man.
And then you find, right?
Yeah.
In New Jersey, there are people arguing,
I should be able to pump my own gas.
In Louisiana, no one ever makes that argument
because everybody pumps their own gas.
Right. Right. Right. When it's when it's just the normal thing, you don't talk about it much.
Right. You only talk about it when somebody's coming to argue with you against it.
Right. Or someone's doing something weird. Right. You might find something about whether people should pump their own gas in Louisiana.
If some guy starts going to gas stations and spraying gas everywhere, like Zoolanger.
Right. Like then it might show up in the local paper. Right.
you
But so, I pointed to evidence that this was an ongoing thing with injudism and was present
in early Christianity.
Some of the best evidence we have comes from the city of Dura Europa because it was pretty
well preserved after its destruction in the latter part of the 3rd century AD, Dura Europa
is a city.
And it gives us a snapshot of...
a pre-constantine third century Roman city in Syria.
And in that city, in the, what that's been excavated,
is the synagogue.
This is a synagogue prior to, and the church we're going to talk about,
everything we're going to talk about, this is prior to the legalization of Christianity.
This is why Christianity is still an illicit religion,
albeit only sporadically persecuted.
This synagogue is covered in iconography still.
And the synagogue dates around 244,
AD 244, covered in iconography.
When I say covered in iconography, I mean
an icon of Samuel anointing David King, right, the kind of iconography
you see in an Orthodox church today, but grounded in the Hebrew Bible.
And again, we know because of the first century synagogues we've excavated
that this is...
not, oh, this weird synagogue in Syria decided to copy the Christians.
Yeah. Right.
Christianity is still in a list of religion. Number one and number two, we have those earlier
synagogues that follow the same pattern. So the deriropos synagogue is just continued
in the synagogue in non-Christian rabbinic Judaism to use a wealth of iconography in their worship space.
Right.
Um, there is
Okay.
is also a house church there from 235.
And part of that house church,
it's a big house, it's like in a state.
And it's a portion of it has been made
into a Christian worship space
and is covered in Christian iconography.
Yeah, and we should mention like,
sometimes when people think of house churches
in the early church, they think of suburban living rooms
and sitting around a coffee table with a guitar or whatever,
No, this is so much a church that it like has a permanent baptisterian it.
Yeah.
And an altar.
Yeah, yeah, exactly.
An altar.
Yeah.
And by the way, you guys, you can Google up images of this, Dura, D-U-R-A, Europa's, E-U-R-O-P-O-S.
Look at this up.
You can see pictures of the synagogue.
You can see pictures of the church.
And look at the iconography.
I can't sit.
It's there for everybody to see.
So don't take our word for it.
Yeah.
And yeah.
And so yes, this assumption, again,
that a house church being simple,
oh, they're just meeting at people's houses, right?
Poor people didn't have houses, right?
Like this, where a big group of people could meet,
this is the wealthy guy's estate,
where he takes a room or a bull building
and converted it for Christian worship.
That's what this is.
And, uh...
When we say converted it for Christian worship, you have to remember what this would have looked like when said guy was a pagan, right?
You gotta get rid of Goozoo's.
Yes, we're not gonna have Goozoo's at a Christian worship space, right?
And they don't just come in and whitewash it.
Right? This is what's important.
Right? If they were iconoclasts, they would have come in and whitewashed it.
Right? It would have just been no iconography.
They get rid of the pagan icon
and they replace it with Christian iconography.
Right.
So when we say that the space was converted,
we don't mean that it was renovated, you know,
by some carpenters and whatever.
I mean, maybe, but we mean converted like a religious conversion.
Yes.
It used to be that this God was worshiped here
and now we're worshiping the true God, you know.
Right. Right.
And to sort of accentuate this point, right?
So we've got the synagogue with iconography.
We've got the house.
church with similar iconography but Christianized right there's also a
mithrayam in deriropos yeah place where you were to mithras mithras right
the mithras cult and guess what's there
Statuary of Mithras like slaying the bull and stuff with altars in front of them.
for making sacrificial offerings.
Yep.
Okay.
So, over here at the Mithrayam, idolatry is going on.
At the synagogue and at the church, idolatry is not going on, but iconography is.
Yeah.
And the Mithrayam is iconography too.
Yes.
There's a bail temple also there as well.
Okay.
I remember correctly in the same city.
Yeah.
Ideology happening there.
So some of our contemporary iconoclass, right, who
are aware of this, right, who are aware of this whole thing.
But don't I think they have a firm idea
that iconography is bad.
And so they're just trying to make arguments.
They're not trying to actually look at this evidence
and learn from it and potentially change their opinion.
That's the only way I can explain it.
Because I don't know how you can look at what we just laid out, especially with the
Mithraya and with the other paganite, and this distinction and the similarity between
the synagogue and the church.
I don't know how you can look at that and come to an iconoclastic presuppose conclusion.
It literally doesn't make sense to me how you can do that.
So I have to say just they're making an iconoclastic argument.
Someone presents this as counter evidence, right?
And they want to neutralize it.
the place they take it is, well this is where iconography started.
Yes, this must be the earliest known piece of iconography.
This is a Syrian phenomenon.
This is just something that starts in Syria.
So it starts in Syria, iconography starts in Syria in the third century, weirdly also including
the synagogue, and then somehow spreads to literally every Christian church on Earth.
With very few objections.
Yes, with very few objections and
to churches that aren't in communion with each other.
Yeah.
Right, because this has to go to the Church of the East.
Right, this has to go to later on as it's spreading to
Calcadonian and non-Calcadonia churches.
I canography everywhere.
Let me add from what we know,
the Arians even use dichotography.
So throw them into
uh less than a century
later after it supposedly started.
That argue makes no sense.
I'm sorry, but it's ridiculous.
It's ridiculous.
It is the best special pleading.
A bizarre kind of special pleading, but like that,
it doesn't hold water.
I'm sorry.
Um, the only, uh, you know, this may be jumping the gun.
We're not done with the half yet.
But frankly, the only feasible rational iconoclastic argument you can make is just that the whole Christian
church was wrong for 1500 years.
Yeah, which I mean, we've heard that argument before.
Right.
There are Protestant folks willing to make that argument, right?
And if you're one of them, right, then throw in iconography to your list of things the church was wrong
about.
for 1,500 years.
Yeah, I mean at least a consistent argument.
Yeah.
But, I mean, even then, even then, right,
you got a lot of problems with Christ in 1st century synagogues.
It's true.
And the apostles.
You still have a lot of trouble with that argument.
But at least it's internally consistent, I guess.
Yeah.
So I mean this other stuff it just doesn't
work folks. So and as we talked about with the shrines and relics and burial sites in the Jewish
context, we of course also find iconography in the catacombs in the burial, Christian burial spaces.
There's people now argue wanting to argue about how much and how often they were used as worship
space but either way, right.
is where the relics are.
So we talked back in the first half about what veneration is.
We said that most of what veneration is is this kind of active viewing.
It's not a participatory viewing.
So veneration strictly, we're just defining the word.
It means to pay the due honor or respect to something or some
one. Yeah, it's it's about honor and respect. That's really what it
what that's re we're not lying. That's really what the word means. Right. And so
way back at the beginning of the episode, remember I gave the example of people,
you know, saluting the flag and singing the national anthem. And I said, that's
veneration. Yeah. Right. The idea there is the people who are doing that are doing
that to show honor and respect to the nation by venerating its icon...
That's what they're doing.
They're literally laws against disrespecting certain elements of the American iconography.
Because it's almost like the honor you pay to an icon passes to its prototype in secular
American thought.
Right?
Like, if you do that, you're disrespecting America.
Right.
Yeah.
So the other piece.
And this is the piece where the rubber meets the road for a lot of contemporary iconoclasts.
It's kissing.
It's the kissing.
Is this a kissing book?
Yeah. I've got to.
And again, I've got to be honest.
And Protestant friends, please join me in being honest about this.
A lot of Protestant objections to stuff in the Orthodox Church
is just that this
that gives them the Hebe GPs. It's okay to have the Hebe GPs. It's okay to feel weird doing something.
Right? Yeah. But that's different than an actual rational objection. Feeling weird about kissing
something, feeling weird about being in the presence of a saint's hand, feeling weird about
the Theotokos because you've had like anti-Roman Catholic stuff about Mary.
drilled into your head your whole life, that's fine, right? There's nothing wrong with
you feeling that and experiencing that, right? But that doesn't mean there's something wrong
with it. That just means you have the HEBGPs about it.
Yeah, and so kissing everybody. In America, we kind of like, you don't say hi by kissing
someone kissing woman's hand is considered to be quite continental.
It's quite continental.
Yeah, or like super formal, super duper duper formal, you know, or a romantic gesture,
right.
But like kissing in a lot of the world is just a way of showing respect.
Like, you know, in both cheeks to greet them.
Yeah.
And France, that's, that's pretty, in the Middle East, they do that too.
on both cheeks, sometimes two times.
sometimes three times depending on where you go.
In the Middle East, adult men who are friends walk around holding hands.
Oh my goodness.
That gives everyone in the United States, he be GBs.
It's okay that it gives you he be GBs, but that doesn't be there's something wrong with
it, for say.
Not just he be's, also GBs.
Yes.
And you know, it's and here's the thing.
Here's the thing kids in the Old Testament.
there's kissing going on with...
with stuff, kissing Torah scrolls.
Right?
Yeah, Jewish circles kissing the Torah scroll.
Kissing the Torah scrolls.
People kiss each other.
You know, St. Paul says, greet one another with a holy kiss.
Greeting with a kiss was a liturgical act
throughout Christian history.
From St. Paul until the present day, frankly,
although the kiss of peace has gotten greatly watered down.
Yeah.
It's now like the handshake of peace
or the nod and grunting.
of Yo but right so I mean kissing is it's just a reality throughout the world that this is very
very normal way to greet to show respect you know it's not part of American culture really
but it's part of almost every other culture right so it's a show of friendship and respect and never
Never, never an active worship.
No.
I-
Dollars don't offer worship to their idol by kissing it.
Yes, they did not form a line and I'll go kiss the statue.
That never happened to paganism.
Yeah, they're putting, they're making sacrifices to it.
You know, that's what's going on with the idolatry.
I've seen lots of people kiss their spouse.
I never thought they were worshiping their spouse.
Yeah.
I've seen them kiss their children on the forehead.
I never thought they were worshiping their child.
Right, so I mean, if kissing is worship,
then that means you should never kiss anything
except God.
God, and how do you do that?
Right, right.
That's, I mean, I don't, how would that work?
Yeah, there's some idea that somehow kissing something
is worshiping is just bizarre.
Yeah.
Right, like,
That's not.
not how idolatry works, that's not how the pagan is at works.
Now I'm sure there is some religion or cult somewhere
that found some way to make kissing an active worship
and I'm sure someone will send it to the email
to tell you guys about it.
Okay.
Right.
Exception to the rule, right?
There's a lot of weird stuff out there.
Yes, yes.
So I'm sure there's somebody, right?
But again, if it gives you the HEBGB, all...
good. Right. Yeah. But again, he bgb's doesn't make it wrong. Except there is one exception
to this by the way. Oh, what is it? No grown man should ever wink at another grown man.
This is wrong. That universally wrong. Think it about it. Trans historically, trans culturally.
No adult man should ever wink at another grown adult man. I mean, there is that money
Python sketch no one in week week knowledge.
No, you know more well, so you could say wink wink nudge nudge. Oh, actually wink. Okay. Okay. Okay.
At he's also sitting beside the person right now looking at him and winking at him. Right. Right.
Yes. No. What about? Okay. So what about a universal abomination? Anyway, an atom. What what about
And we got this question in our group recently. Like what about wonder working icons?
Someone asked, you know, you put beautiful clothing on a one...
working icon, you sometimes will put flowers like are these offerings being made offerings to
his like an idol, like clothing and feeding and bathing an idol. So how about that? I mean,
is that the Achilles heel of the pool? I kind of do you look thing we got going on?
So yeah, first of all putting those things around it right is just decorating it.
That's right.
And the worship space itself, as we said, from the Tabernacle.
along is at an iconic function, right?
Therefore, if there's a problem with decorating an icon,
there would be a problem with decorating a worship space.
Or decorating anything.
Well, yeah.
Because I mean, again, like if you're going to say
that decorating yourself, you're the icon of Christ.
Yeah, yeah.
If you're going to say decorating is worship,
then you can't have decoration.
So don't take care of yourself, people.
It's idolatry.
Um, uh, yeah.
But even your most white washed plane Baptist church on earth,
right, they decorated a little.
You get the felt banners for something, right?
You get the, you know.
And people dress up to go to church.
But more importantly than that, right?
A wonder working icon is by definition
an icon through which God has done things.
specifically worked wonders, right?
I think through which God has worked, right?
So this is very firmly the snake in the wilderness,
not the snake in second kings.
Yeah, right.
The snake in the wilderness is literally
a wonderworking icon.
Yes, it is an image,
it's a great image through which God worked healings.
It was God doing the healing, right?
But he chose for his own reasons to do it through that image.
And we believe, this is basic Christianity.
God works through means.
God does things in the world through people.
This is man being made in the image of God.
So God works through people.
He works through the saints.
Even when they're not physically alive anymore.
works through material thing.
See our whole sacrament series, right? That's what the sacraments are all about.
It's got working through material things, baptism, he works through water.
The Eucharist, he works through bread and wine, right? God works through us in the world
and God can work through icons if he so chooses, right?
And as a history of doing it, see book of numbers, right?
And that's if we exclude people as
icons, which of course they are. Right. And really ultimately what this comes down to is our old
enemy plateenism again. Right.
Curses plate nice again. Um, because the real iconoclast arguments, right, are ultimately
not Christian arguments.
Not that those people aren't Christians.
That's not what I'm saying.
Some of them maybe not, I don't know, but that's not what I'm saying. That's not what I'm getting at. I'm getting at they're not arguments that proceed from Christianity as such.
Right.
So I can say make an argument from the Bible about whether something is ethically right or wrong, or I can make a different type of argument.
I can do a Kant and I can say, right?
categorical imperative, right? What would happen if everyone did that?
You know society would descend into chaos. So if we don't want everyone to do that, that means you shouldn't do that, right?
That's not a Christian argument, right?
That's not saying it's anti-Christian or evil or something, right? I don't know that it holds up, but but
Right, right? It's not a Christian argument. A Christian argument against say steal.
Right, let's say that's what we're doing, right? If everyone stole everything would follow so you shouldn't steal
Right
If I come to you with a Christian arguing against stealing I might point to one of the ten commandments and then I might say
Right into quote Christ talking about
You know not being concerned
Right about somebody tells me they're gonna steal because they're worried they don't have enough money
And I say well, they're not worried about what you'll eat or what you will wear right?
it. Seek first the Kingdom of God and to seek the Kingdom of God.
of God, you need to keep the commandments of God. That's a Christian argument, right? So
that's what I mean when I say they're not Christian arguments, right? Christian arguments
go the other way, right? The incarnation goes the other way. There's no one saying because
of the incarnation, we can't use iconography anymore. Right. Those aren't the arguments.
The arguments are essentially non-Christian arguments.
And I'm not including here,
arguments that are just made out of ignorance,
like Calvin, who just didn't know a bunch of things
about history, because he couldn't,
because he lived in the 16th century in Switzerland.
So there's arguments made out of ignorance, right?
Of people who are trying to make Christian arguments,
but they just lack data and information.
And there's kind of a,
It's kind of a thing.
of the children argument, but it's, you know, oh, think of the idiots, right? We can't
have any iconography because there's people out there so stupid they'll do an idolatry,
right? So there's that which is also not per se a Christian argument. But the core of
these iconoclastic arguments when you really get into the meaty ones, right? The serious ones,
they're grounded in plate-ness.
They're grounded in a rejection of, for example,
call.
the ability of the divine of God to work through and be represented by the material.
Right. Including in the incarnation. That's why that's where the rubber sort of meets the road.
Because the incarnation is one of the things that wrecks Platonism.
Yeah, right because
Christ, right, when Christ is standing before the apostles, the person they're
seeing with their eyes and hearing with their ears and touching with their hands,
right, is not the shadow of an image of God, which is what he would have to be
if you're a playtinist. Right.
So the incarnation destroys Platonic arguments again. That's why the church fathers who knew their stuff
Way better than me
Went there to attack the iconoclastic arguments, right?
It's a rejection of the sensory. It's a rejection of what we can see and hear and touch
This is what St. Gregory of Paul St. Gregory Paulmas got into with Barlam, right? Barlam says no no no no no you can't
see the vision.
of Christ with your eyes.
Yeah.
That's what your mind,
when you're mind,
forget the body, forget the body.
Right?
The grounded in rejection
of the goodness of creation ultimately.
Shout out to Robin Phillips book.
Right?
Of the material creation.
In which iconography exists?
Right?
Why is it a rejection of the material creation?
Material creation is where iconography exists.
It's experienced with our physical eyes, right?
And the iconic plastic arguments fundamentally
say that what I see with my eyes,
even when looking at iconography,
and what iconography can depict,
and what I can meditate on and participate on there by,
is an obstacle,
an obstacle to some kind of spiritual or intellectual
a cent.
toward God. Yeah, it gets in the way. I mean, this is one of the objections as well to
the communion of saints is that they get in the way. Right. Right. And that's platonic thinking.
It's always either or it can't be both and diversity. You always have something better and
something worse and the worst should be rejected in favor of the better.
And that's why it lends itself to the kind of aristocratic rationalism we've talked about
before. Right? Where you get the people who are like, well, okay, maybe iconography because
you know, there's all those dumb people, you know, who might need to look at pictures.
Half of them are probably illiterate, but those of us who have elevated ourselves to this
higher level of insight and intellect.
Or the other way.
like, well, you know, we, we who are educated can understand how
iconography and venerating it is not idolatry, but, but I bet a
lot of those peasants, you know, those uneducated people, they're
probably actually, you know, being idolaters and they don't
really know it. Yeah. Yeah. But again, like, as we, as we've
mentioned, you know, in the ancient world, where almost everybody's
literate, everyone understood this distinction.
Without any problem right and what all of these kind of tax on all of these metaphys platonic metaphysics
What what all of them have become what all of them do is they undermine the incarnation they undermine the reality of the faith
That it is worked out in real time in the world
both in the sense of
the events of scripture not being real.
and going forward in the sense that my salvation is not worked out in real time with how I relate to other humans.
But it's some kind of intellectual matter, matter of a scent.
Or in some cases, I don't even have to do anything.
However that's seen, it's definitely not something that plays out in real time, in material terms, on this earth,
where me giving a cup of cold water to someone
in need is what's going to bring about my salvation and potentially allow me some day to see God,
which would be what Scripture says.
You know, as we were talking about, particularly about wonderworking icons, I started thinking
about the...
several. Well, I mean, I think maybe at this point in my life, I can say many, the many
wonderworking icons that I've been around. I mean, there was one monastery on Monatos
that had seven wonderworking icons and that one monastery. And of course, we've inherited
many when we were there. But we have them here in the U.S., too. You know, there's the
the Carthiotes in Taylor, Pennsylvania, just about an hour.
where I live.
The Hawaiian, if you're on icon that tours around,
it's from Hawaii, but gets around a lot.
And both these icons are mirstrimming,
meaning that they give off this light, fragrant oil
that often when people are anointed with it,
with prayer, they are healed of diseases,
sometimes really intractable diseases.
Um,
priest who is the keeper of one of those icons he has
notebooks upon notebooks filled with the miracle stories that he's been told related to
that particular icon and
um
You know, I get asked sometimes like is that is that real
the deal, occasionally people will say things like there must be some kind of mechanism.
pumping that stuff out. And I mean, has it ever been faked?
Yes. There are fakes.
They're been fakes. But they are not all. Indeed, I have been present in with
and in a couple of cases watched as the flow of murder
sped up during a church service and then slowed down when the service was over.
In one case, it was exuding so much mer that we had to continually mop it up off the table
where the icon was resting so that it wouldn't just simply all dump on the floor.
That much mer was coming off of it.
In several cases, these icons are kept in cases.
in cases that open and close.
basically to protect them into their easier to transport and also frankly so that the
murder doesn't just dump everywhere, right? And there's been a couple of times where I've
seen the icon in its case with the lid closed and the lid of course is glass on the front
so that people can see the icon still and venerate it through the glass. And you know since
I was one of the serving priests I was standing right next to and I was looking at it and
and I watched her.
form on the glass. Not like streamed down on top of it, but like form in the middle of
it and then drip down. And I don't know how you can get glass to do that through some
kind of artificial means. I don't know how you could do that. You know, it's the real
deal. It's the real deal. And you know, I've been asked like, well, why why is why is
is this a thing? Why does this happen? And it's not it's not to prove anything.
It's simply a gift from God, his love for his people, his healing for his people.
Right? And all of this points to one of the central points of our discussion about
iconography and why it is so radically different from idolatry.
the spirit of a God becoming located in an object.
And so then therefore the object is worshiped
because it is understood to be the body of that God.
So everything is focused on that object.
It's localized in the object.
The worship goes into the object and stops there
because that's where the God is.
The God is inside it.
Right?
Iconography is not a...
stop. The honor does not stop at the icon. Any honor that's paid to it does not stop there.
The very clear theology of Orthodox Church is that the honor paid to the icon passes to the
prototype. In other words, the icon functions as something through which we show our love and
and respect and honor to God, to His saints, whatever.
But also, and this is apparent, especially through these wonderworking icons, it is something
through which, again, through which the love and the power and the healing and the salvation
of God comes.
God acts through it.
We don't believe that wonderworking icons are like magical talismans that have power within
them.
You know, they are rather something through which God acts.
It all comes from God. The healing is from God, the love is from God, the miracle is from God.
It's not located in the item.
It's not.
And so I think that
you know, as we said that
that iconography in the Christian context, the biblical context,
context is really a rebuke of idolatry because idolatry is profoundly stupid because idolatry
thinks that God's live inside objects and that you can control them through those objects.
That's what idolatry is.
Whereas as it says in scripture, God does not dwell in temples made by hands.
He doesn't dwell in anything made by hands, not in the sense of like being trapped inside
it.
that he's not saying God doesn't dwell in tuples made by hands to say that God is everywhere except in
that temple, right? Because God is everywhere. And indeed God makes himself known in that temple
in a particular way, in his present and dwelling, in dwelling in that temple in particular way. But
when we say, and when he says that God is not dwell in tuples made by hands, it is to say that God
cannot be trapped by idolatry. That's what that means. Right? And so since we know...
that God acts through icons. And again, you can set aside all of the post, you know, new
testament icons. You can set aside all of that and just simply look at the fact that this
happens in the Old Testament, the Bronze Serpent, the Ark, the Tabernacle, and so on. God
does act through icons, and it is a rebuke of idolatry. It's a rebuke of idolatry.
It is a restory.
creation of the creation, the way that God made it to be, that the creation would be a conduit
of God's love for us and that we would show Him our love through the way that we relate
to Him through that creation.
To all of it, yes, in general, but especially to the original icon of God, our fellow humans.
So the idea of doing these last two episodes on idolatry and iconography respectively,
kind of spun out of some commentary we did somewhat on the side, not entirely,
during the episode on the last judgment in our eschatology series.
and in the
that context, we're talking about how the principle at work in the parable of the sheep of the goats,
the parable of the last judgment in St. Matthew's Gospel is that of iconography, right,
that every human, because they are the icon of God, whatever you have done, or you haven't done to the least of these,
done, you have done to Christ, right? Who is the judge? And
And so we talked about that in that context, how whatever we do to or fail to do for
any of our fellow human beings, we are doing or failing to do for God.
And St. John, in 1 John 420, you can insert your own joke there.
And he says...
very seriously, that the person who says that he loves God but hates his brothers a liar.
And then he goes on to say, because if you cannot love your brother, whom you have seen,
how will you love God who you have not seen?
And that latter part is kind of counter.
intuitive if we really stop and think about it. Because most people, I think, for
honest, would have to say, well no, I think it's way easier to love God than to
love a lot of my fellow human beings. Right? Like, if I can't love this guy
who's an annoying jerk, who's rude to me, or says or does these horrible things to
if I can't live here, I can't...
love God that doesn't make any sense right God created me God loves me right it's easy to to love God
but so that disjunction between what say John is saying and what we're saying it's a John uses
that argument as proof for something else he said so he acts as if it should be self-evident
it.
Reveal something terrible to us.
Feel something terrible to us.
If we find it very easy to love God or to love Jesus, it's probably because the God
or the Jesus whom we find it so easy to love isn't real.
The God we say we love, the God that we've attached emotional feelings of affection to,
or to whom we run when we get into trouble.
Isn't the actual God who exists and created the universe at some abstraction?
It's some concept.
We talked last episode about how concepts can become idols in our head.
And we've made it very lovable, very friendly.
We may have, like those icons, the color asked about, turned them into this kindly old man
who just loves everybody.
once again this is a big hug
Or the Jesus in our head may well be our own personal Jesus.
It cares.
It never has a harsh word for us.
Let alone anybody else except maybe once it will offer some people we don't like or who make us mad.
That, as I said, is terrible to realize.
That is something that should fill us with the deepest kind of concern.
What?
Why is it that in actuality it's hard to love God if we can't love our neighbor?
Well, in order to love God, we first have to come to know Him.
Not know things about Him, not come to an idea of Him, not formulate a concept of Him,
but come to actually know Him, come to actually know Christ.
to do.
that we have to encounter him. We have to meet him. We have to meet him and we have to spend time with him.
Where do we meet him? We meet him in his icons, who are those other people who are all around us.
And so if I can't bring myself to love the person who I meet out on the street,
who smells bad is asking me for money and is probably just going to spend it on something he shouldn't spend it on.
If I can't love that person in a concrete way,
by trying to actually do something to help them, by giving them a little of my time and attention,
by giving them a little bit of love.
And if I continue to have that inability throughout my life,
I can go through my whole life without ever meeting God.
It doesn't matter what I believe about him or think about him or claim to know about him,
I never will have met him.
Since I haven't met him, I won't know him.
And since I don't know him, I can't love him.
On the other hand, when I see every interaction I have with other people, as interactions with
icons of God, then every one of them is an opportunity for me to meet God, for me to
encounter him.
for me to spend time with him, for me to come to know him
over the course of my life, through doing this over and over and over again as the saints did.
And as I meet him over and over again, as I spend time with him, as I come to know him,
and come to know him ever more deeply, then I can start to love him.
And then I can start to truly love him, truly experience his love and...
return. But the medium through which that happens is my fellow human beings. The medium through
which that happens are his icons who surround me every day. And that's why that, these day-to-day,
material, very simple, very sensory encounters. That's where my salvation is worked out.
Not in some platonic realm of ideas, not in holding all the right opinions theological
and otherwise, not in being a scholar, not by going to the right church.
But that's where that's the arena where my salvation has worked out, which puts a lie to
all those other things.
This is why it's possible for someone as we're told in the Gospels to go and work miracles
and preach and cast out demons in the name of Christ and be told, be gone I never knew
you.
This is also why it's possible for anyone, regardless of where and when they were born,
abilities, mental and physical and otherwise possible for everyone to ins-
We stand before Him and we come to know Him well and to share in His love.
Those are my thoughts.
Amen.
Well, that's our show for tonight.
Thank you for listening, everyone.
If you can get through to a slide we'd like to hear from you.
You can email us at LordofSpearedShadAncientFace.com.
You can message us at our Facebook page or you can leave us on Facebook.
We'll see you next time.
www.facetanetionfeith.com
You can message us at our Facebook page
or you can leave us...
a voice mill at SpeakPipe.com slash Lord of Spirits. And if you have basic questions about
Orthodox Christianity or need help finding a parish, head over to Orthodox intro.org.
And join us for our live broadcast in the second and fourth Thursdays of the month at 7 p.m.
Eastern 4 p.m. Pacific. You know, I've been looking so long at these pictures of you
that I almost believed that they're real. And if you are on Facebook, unlike Father
Steve, and follow our page, join our discussion group, leave ratings and reviews on all the
the appropriate places. Most importantly share this show with a friend.
and who's going to benefit from it.
And finally, be sure to go to www.inxfordfaith.com
stroke support and help make sure we and lots
of other AFR podcasters stay on the air.
I've been looking so long with my pictures of you
that I almost believe that the pictures are all I can feel.
Thank you, good night, and may God bless you always,
and we'll see you in two weeks at the Lord of Spirits Conference.
You've been listening to the l-
of spirits, with Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick, and Father Stephen
De Young, a listener-supported presentation of ancient faith radio.
And I beheld, and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne, and the beasts,
and the elders, and the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000, and thousands of thousands,
saying with a loud voice, worthy as the land that was slain to receive power, and riches,
wisdom and strength and honor.
and glory and blessing.
Revelation chapter 5 verses 11 through 12.